Stop now.
不许动
Tell me where it is.
告诉我那东西在哪里
You and your brethren possess what is not rightfully yours.
你和你的兄弟们占有了 不属于你们的东西
I don't know what you are talking about.
我不懂你在说什么
Is it a secret you will die for?
你想为这个秘密送命罗？
- Please. - As you wish.
- 随便你 - 如你所愿
Wait!
等等
My God, forgive me.
上帝啊，宽恕我
In the sacristy...
圣苏比教堂的圣器室内有一条玫瑰线
Beneath the Rose.
就在玫瑰线下面
Thank you.
谢谢
Symbols are a language that can help us understand our past.
符号是一门语言 能帮助我们理解过去
As the saying goes, a picture says a thousand words...
正如谚语所说 “一图抵千言”
...but which words?
但究竟是怎样的千言呢？
Interpret for me, please, this symbol. First thing that comes to mind.
请哪位给我说说此符号的意思 要第一感觉
- Hatred, racism. - Ku Klux Klan.
- 仇恨，种族主义 - 三K党
Yes, yes, interesting. But they would disagree with you in Spain.
好的，很有意思 但西班牙人有不同的见解
There, they are robes worn by priests.
在那里，这是牧师穿的长袍
Now this symbol. Anyone?
现在来看看这符号，有谁自愿？
Evil.
邪恶
In English, please.
请说英语
Devil's pitchfork.
魔鬼的草叉
Poor, poor Poseidon.
可怜的海神波塞冬
That is his trident. A symbol of power to millions of the ancients.
这是他的三叉戟 对于很多古人这代表着力量
Now this symbol.
这个符号呢
- Madonna and child. - Faith. Christianity.
- 圣母与圣子 - 信仰，基督教
No. No, it's the pagan god Horus and his mother, Isis...
错，错，这是异教徒的神 霍鲁斯和他的母亲艾西斯
...centuries before the birth of Christ.
基督诞生之前数个世纪 他们就存在了
Understanding our past determines actively...
对过去的了解程度决定了
...our ability to understand the present.
我们对现在的理解能力
So how do we sift truth from belief?
我们怎样分辨信仰和事实？
How do we write our own histories, personally or culturally...
我们怎样写下自己的历史 描述个人和文化上的特征
...and thereby define ourselves?
以此定位出自我呢？
How do we penetrate years, centuries, of historical distortion...
我们怎样在历史长河大浪淘沙
...to find original truth?
找到初始的真相呢？
Tonight, this will be our quest.
这就是我们今晚的话题
I still think that his whole take on phi was a little far-fetched.
我还是觉得它对希腊字母phi 的理解有点牵强
I don't think so. I think that the golden ratio is everywhere in nature.
我不这么认为，我觉得 黄金分割在自然界比比皆是
Sure, I can do that.
当然，乐意效劳.
My son is a student of yours at Harvard.
我儿子是你在哈佛的学生
- Michael Culp? He adores you. - Oh, yeah.
- 他叫迈克尔・克尔普，他爱死你了 - 哦，是吗
He says you're the best teacher he's ever had.
他说你是他见过的最好的老师
Ms. Culp, I think I already gave Michael an A-minus.
克尔普女士，我记得 我已经给了迈克一个A减了
He told me. Thank you.
他告诉我了，谢谢
Mr. Langdon?
兰登先生
Hi.
嗨
Bonjour, professor.
你好，教授
I'm Lieutenant Collet from DCPJ. A kind of French FBI.
我是法国中央司法警察部的科莱上尉 相当于美国的联邦调查局
Will you take a look at this photo, please?
你能看看这张照片吗？
My police chief, Capitaine Fache, had hoped...
我的警务局长，法希警长
...considering your expertise and the markings on the body...
觉得以你的专长和这尸体上的记号
...you might assist us.
你能帮到我们
Will you excuse me a moment?
失陪一下
I was supposed to have drinks with him.
我本该和他喝一杯的
Yes, we know.
是的，我们知道
We found your name in his daily planner.
我们在他的日程安排上 发现了你的名字
He never showed. I waited for over an hour.
可他没出现，我等了一个多小时
Why would someone do this to him?
为什么有人会这样对他？
Oh, you misunderstand, professor.
哦，你可能误解了，教授
He was shot, yes.
他是被枪杀的
But what you see in the photograph...
而你在这照片上见到的情景
...Monsieur Sauniere did to himself.
则是索尼埃先生自己制造的
Teacher, all four are dead.
导师，四个人都死了
The senechaux and the Grand Master himself.
包括长老们和大师本人
Then I assume you have the location.
那你一定找到具体位置了吧
Confirmed by all.
他们全部都确认过
Independently.
而且每个人是独立确认的
I had feared the Priory's penchant for secrecy might prevail.
我本来还担心隐修会能守住这个秘密呢
The prospect of death is strong motivation.
死亡面前人人都会低头
It is here.
就在这里
In Paris, Teacher.
在巴黎，导师
It hides beneath the Rose in Saint-Sulpice.
藏在圣苏比教堂的玫瑰线下面
You will go forth, Silas.
继续吧，塞拉斯
I chastise my body.
我鞭打自己的身体
Capitaine Fache is waiting for you.
法希警长在等你
Okay.
好的
- Mr. Langdon. - Yes.
- 兰登先生 - 我是
I'm Captain Bezu Fache.
我是贝祖・法希警长
You like our pyramid?
你喜欢我们的金字塔吗？
It's magnificent.
非常宏伟
A scar on the face of Paris.
巴黎脸上的一块疤而已
After me, please.
请跟我来
It's the pairing of those two pyramids.
这一对金字塔
It's unique.
是独一无二的
The two are geometric echoes.
它们是几何上的镜面反射
Fascinating.
很有意思
I'm not sure how much help I'm gonna be here this evening.
不知道今晚我能帮多大忙
How well did you know the curator?
你对馆长有多了解？
Not at all. We met only once.
不太多，我们只见过一面
We were on a...
我们曾参加...
On a panel together.
参加一个座谈会
Something is funny?
有什么有趣的话题吗？
We didn't agree on much.
我们的见解不太相同
Frankly, I was surprised when he contacted me.
说实话，他联系我的时候我很吃惊
Could we take the stairs?
我们可以走楼梯吗？
So Sauniere requested tonight's meeting.
那么这次会面是索尼埃要求的了
Yes.
是的
How? Did he call you?
怎么要求的？打电话？
E-mail. He heard I was in Paris.
用电子邮件，他听说我在巴黎
Had something to discuss.
说有事要和我讨论
What?
什么事？
You seem uncomfortable.
你看起来很不舒服
- Are any of those real? - Of course not.
- 这里挂的有真品吗？ - 当然没有
So you know something of security procedures.
看来你对保安措施有点了解啊
Well, I know video surveillance in a museum this size is cost-prohibitive.
我知道这么大的博物馆 用摄像头监控是太贵了
Most now rely on containment.
大多数博物馆现在都靠密封装置了
Yes, forget about keeping the criminals out.
是的，现在我们不再把罪犯关到门外了
Now we keep them in.
我们把他们关门里
The Grand Gallery. This is where you found the body.
大画廊，你就是在这找到尸体的
How would you know that?
你怎么知道？
I recognize the parquet floor from the Polaroid. It's unmistakable.
从宝丽莱快照上我认出了镶花地板 绝不会错的
Dear God.
哦，上帝啊
Let's cover the talking points again, Your Eminence.
再来回顾一下谈话要点吧 红衣主教阁下
Many call Opus Dei a brainwashing cult.
很多人称天主事工会 是洗脑的宗教派别
Others, an ultraconservative Christian secret society.
其他人认为是非常保守的 基督教秘密组织
- We are a simple Catholic church. - Simple?
- 我们只是个简朴的天主教派别 - 简朴？
With a brand-new $47-million headquarters in Manattan.
居然能在曼哈顿建一座 四千七百万美元的新总部
Our followers are generous, should we apologize for that?
我们的信徒很慷慨 我们难道要为此道歉？
Perhaps a less defensive tack, Your Eminence.
换种不那么拒人于千里的 说法比较好，阁下
The press continue to be harsh with us.
媒体对我们的评价还是不怎样
We are not Cafeteria Catholics.
我们不是那种随便的天主教徒
We don't pick and choose which rules to follow.
我们不会挑挑拣拣 选择某些教规执行
We follow doctrine. Rigorously.
我们严格执行每条教义
Does doctrine necessarily include vows of chastity, tithing...
教义一定要包括独身誓言，什一税
...and atonement for sins through self-flagellation and the cilice?
和通过自我鞭打 与穿粗布衣服来赎罪吗？
Many of our followers are married. Many of them have families.
我们有很多教徒结婚，有家庭
Only a small proportion choose to live ascetically...
只有很小一部分选择过苦行僧的生活
...in the cloisters of our residential halls.
他们住在我们的修道院里
But we are all united in God's work around the world.
但我们都因为上帝的神迹走到了一起
Surely that is an admirable way to lead one's life.
这种生活是多么令人羡慕啊
Why are some media referring to Opus Dei as "God's mafia"?
为什么有些媒体把 天主事工会比作“上帝黑帮”呢？
Obviously, some people fear what they don't understand.
很明显，某些人害怕 他们不理解的东西
And because the war finally draws to a close.
还有，这场战争终于要结束了
- Bishop, we need to stay on message. - That will be all, Michael, thank you.
- 主教，我们不能信口开河 - 到此为止吧，迈克，谢谢
Aringarosa.
阿林加洛沙
Silas has succeeded. The legend is true.
塞拉斯成功了，那个传说是真的
It hides beneath the Rose.
那东西藏在玫瑰线下面
My part of our bargain is nearly fulfilled.
我这部分约定差不多完成了
I meet the council in an hour.
我一个小时以内就会和委员会见面
I will have your money tonight, Teacher.
我今晚会把你的钱准备好的，导师
The Vitruvian Man.
维特鲁威人
It's one of Leonardo da Vinci's most famous sketches.
列奥纳多・达・芬奇最出名的画作之一
And the star on his skin?
他皮肤上这个星形呢？
A pentacle.
五角星
And its meaning?
有什么含义？
The pentacle is ancient.
五角星的历史很悠远
Symbols carry different meanings in different settings.
符号在不同情况下有不同意义
This symbol, professor. This setting.
就这个符号，教授，在现在这个情况下
The pentacle is a pagan religious icon.
五角星是异教徒的象征
Devil worship.
恶魔崇拜
No. No, no, no. The pentacle before that.
不，不对，是那之前的五角星
This is a symbol for Venus.
这代表女神维纳斯
It represents the female half of all things.
它代表世间万物的阴性的一半
It's a concept called "the divine goddess" by religious historians.
宗教历史学家称之为女神
You are telling me that Sauniere's last act on earth...
你是说索尼埃生前最后的举动
...was to draw a goddess symbol on his chest? Why?
就是在自己胸口上 划一个女神的符号？为什么？
Captain Fache, obviously I can't tell you why.
法希警长，很明显我无法告诉你为什么
I can tell you he, as well as anyone, knows the meaning of this symbol...
我可以告诉你，他和任何人 都知道这符号的含义
...and it has nothing to do with worshiping the devil.
而那与恶魔崇拜无关
- Is that so? - Yes.
- 是这样吗？ - 没错
Then...
那么...
...what do you make of this?
你怎么解释这个？
"O, Draconian devil. Oh, lame saint."
啊，严酷的恶魔 噢，瘸腿的圣徒
It's a phrase. Doesrt mean anything, not to me.
一句短语，没啥意思 起码我不懂
What would you do if you had such limited time to send a message?
如果你只有这么有限的时间 来发消息，你怎么做？
Well, I suppose I'd try to identify my killer.
这个，我想我会试着指明凶手
Precisely.
对极了
So, professor...
那，教授...
Officer Neveu.
奈芙警官
Please, pardon the interruption.
请原谅我打断你们的谈话
This is not the time.
现在不是时候
I received the crime-scene jpegs at headquarters...
我在总部收到一幅犯罪现场的图片
...and I've deciphered the code.
我已经破译了密码
It's a Fibonacci sequence.
是斐波那契数列
That's the code Sauniere left on the floor.
那就是索尼埃留在地板上的密码
Headquarters sent me to explain, captain.
总部派我来解释，警长
It is the Fibonacci sequence.
确实是斐波那契数列
The numbers are out of order.
只是数字的顺序打乱了
But before that, I have an urgent message for Professor Langdon.
但在此之前，我有一条紧急的讯息 要告诉兰登教授
Right?
对吧？
Pardon me?
嗯？你说什么
I'm Sophie Neveu, French police, Cryptology.
我叫索菲・奈芙，法国警察 专攻密码学
Your embassy called Division.
你们大使馆给局里打了电话
I'm sorry, monsieur, they said it was a matter of life and death.
对不起，先生，他们说这事关生死
This is the number of your embassy's messaging service.
这是你们大使馆留言服务的电话
Well, thank you.
哦，谢谢
Hello, you've reached the home of Sophie Neveu.
你好，你拨通的是索菲・奈芙的家庭电话
Miss Neveu? This...
奈芙小姐？这...
No. That's the right number.
没错，那就是正确的号码
You have to dial an access code to pick up your messages.
你得按接入码才能收到你的留言
But I'm getting...
但我收到...
It's a three-digit code. It's on the paper I gave you.
是个三位数接入码 就在我给你的那张纸上
Professor Langdon, do not react to this message.
兰登教授，对此留言不要有任何反应
You must follow my directions very closely and, above all...
你必须完全按照我的指示去做 更关键的是...
...reveal nothing to Captain Fache.
决不要告诉法希警长任何事情
You are in grave danger.
你身处于极大的危险中
Church of Saint-Sulpice.
圣苏比教堂
Good evening, Sister.
晚上好，嬷嬷
I need you to show someone our church tonight.
我需要你今晚给某人 展示一下我们的教堂
Of course, Father.
没问题，神父
But so late?
但是这么晚
Wouldrt tomorrow...?
明天不是...
This is a request from an important bishop of Opus Dei.
这是天主教事工会 一位重要的主教的要求
It would be my pleasure.
我很荣幸
There's been an accident. A friend.
是场事故，我的一位朋友...
I have to fly home in the morning.
我明天一早得飞回家
I see.
懂了
Is there a restroom I could use? I just wanna splash some water on my face.
我可以用一下洗手间吗？ 我想往脸上淋点水
Yes.
当然
She said it is meaningless.
她说这毫无意义
Mathematical joke.
是数字玩笑
Is it meaningless?
真的没有意义吗？
I'll take another look when I come back.
等我回来我再看看
I'm sorry. Of course.
对不起，请便
Do you have a message from Sauniere?
你有索尼埃的留言吗？
What are you talking about?
你在说什么？
Crazy old man.
老疯子
You have me confused with someone else.
你把我和其他什么人搞混了
I was asked to come here and consult.
我是应邀来此提供参考意见的
No, you are sous surveillance cachee.
不，你被秘密监视了
Yes, and...
是的，不过...
What?
什么？
Bring the suspect to the crime scene and hope he incriminates himself.
把嫌犯带到犯罪现场，期望他们能露出马脚
Suspect?
嫌犯？
Check your jacket pocket.
查查你的外衣口袋
Just look.
查查看
GPS tracking dot.
全球定位系统追踪器
Accurate within two feet anywhere on the globe.
可以定位全球任何位置 误差仅两英尺
The agent who picked you up slipped it into your jacket...
接你来的那位特工放进你外衣的
...in case you tried to run.
以防你逃跑
We have you on a little leash, professor.
我们对你进行了一点监控，教授
Why would I try to run? I didn't do anything.
我为什么要逃跑？我什么都没做
So, what do you think about the fourth line of text...
那你对这第四行字有何看法？
...Fache wiped clean before you arrived?
法希在你来之前擦干净的
He brought you here to force a confession, Professor Langdon.
他带你来这里是逼你认罪的 兰登教授
He's still in there? What's he doing?
他还在那？他在干嘛？
Fache isn't even looking for other suspects, okay?
法希甚至没寻找其他嫌疑犯 懂了吗？
He is sure you're guilty.
他认定你是有罪的
When did Sauniere contact you?
索尼埃什么时候和你联系的？
- Today? - Yes, yes.
- 今天？ - 是的
What time? What time?
何时？
At 3. Around 3. Three.
三点，差不多三点
The gallery alarm was triggered at 8. You were...
画廊的警报是8点被启动的，你在哪？
- I was giving a lecture. - At 9.
- 我在作一场讲演 - 那是9点
You had the privacy light on in your hotel room until 8:30, right?
你旅馆房间的请勿打扰灯 直到8点半还是亮的，对吧？
We call Fache "the Bull." Once he starts, he doesn't stop.
我们管法希叫“公牛” 他一开始就不会停的
He can arrest you and detain you for months while he builds a case.
他会逮捕你，拘留你几个月 好让他找到罪证
And by then whatever Sauniere wanted you to tell me will be useless.
到那时索尼埃要你告诉我的 都将毫无意义
Stop it! Just stop!
女士，别说了
Who are you?
你是谁？
What are you talking about? Tell you what?
你在说什么？你要我告诉你什么？
Maybe who really killed him.
比如到底是谁杀了他
The Fibonacci sequence.
斐波那契数列
I believe Sauniere wrote it...
我相信索尼埃写下它们
...so his investigation would include cryptographers.
是为了能让密码学家参予到调查中来
That's quite a leap, isn't it?
这逻辑跳跃有点大啊
No.
不
And the letters.
看看这些字母
"P.S."
“P.S.”
P.S., postscript.
P.S.，附言？
"Princess Sophie." Yeah. Silly, I know.
是“索菲公主”，很滑稽，我知道
But I was only a girl when I lived with him.
但我和他住在一起的时候 我只是个小女孩
Jacques Sauniere was my grandfather.
雅克・索尼埃是我的祖父
Apparently, it was his dying wish that we meet.
很明显，他的遗愿就是让我们见面
If you help me understand why...
如果你能帮我搞清他的目的
...I will get you to your embassy, where we cannot arrest you.
我就带你去你的大使馆 在那我们就没法逮捕你了
Fache was never gonna let me just stroll out of here, was he?
法希不会让我就这么 溜达出去的，对吧？
No.
不会
If we are to get away from here, we must find another way.
如果我们要离开这里 我们必须得另寻方法
What exactly do you propose?
你到底有什么建议？
Sauniere was reading his book.
索尼埃也在读他的书
"Blood trail."
“血路”
Excuse me, captain.
对不起，警长
Crypto called. They identified the code.
密码部打电话来了，他们解开了那密码
Neveu told us already.
奈芙已经告诉我们了
I should have fired her on the spot, barging in like that.
我应该当场把她开除 敢那么和我讨价还价
Yes.
是的
Except they didn't send Neveu.
只是他们没派索菲・奈芙来
What?
什么？
Captain, look at this.
警长，看这个
He jumped!
他跳出去了！
Shit.
妈的
He's moving again. And fast.
他又动了，非常快
He must be in a car.
他一定在车里
He's going south on Pont du Carrousel.
他在卡鲁塞尔桥上向南移动
Bastard.
混蛋
That cop will check the whole lower floor.
那个警察会检查整个下层大厅
I will only take a moment.
我只会花一点时间
Of course.
没问题
He is much older than I remember.
他比我记忆中要老的多
I hadrt seen or spoken to him in a very long time.
我许久没有见过他 和他说过话了
He phoned my office today. Several times.
他今天给我办公室 打了好几个电话
He said it was a matter of life and death.
他说这事关生死
I thought it was another trick to get back in touch.
我以为那只是另一个花招 好让我们恢复联系
It seems when he couldn't speak to me...
看起来他找不到我
...he reached out to you.
就去找了你
Whatever he needed so badly to say...
不管他这么急切的想说什么
...he found neither of us in time.
我们两个他一个都没及时找到
- Wait a minute. - Professor?
- 等等 - 教授？
Come on.
妈的
It can't be that easy.
不可能这么简单
This is wrong. Yeah. See? This is wrong.
错了，是的，看，完全错了
The Fibonacci numbers only make sense when they're in order.
斐波那契数列只有 按正常排序才是有意义的
These are scrambled.
而这些数杂乱无章
If he was trying to reach out, maybe he was doing it in code.
如果他在找人帮忙 可能他是用密语来做的
Would you hold this, please?
请你拿着这个好吗？
This phrase is meaningless.
这句话毫无意义
Unless you assume these letters are out of order too.
除非假定这些字母顺序也是乱的
An anagram.
乱序字谜
You have eidetic memory?
你能过目不忘？
Not quite. But I can pretty much remember what I see.
没那么强，但我能把看到的记个差不离
Anagram is right.
确实是乱序字谜
"O, Draconian devil. Oh, lame saint" becomes:
啊，严酷的恶魔，噢，瘸腿的圣徒 能变成
"Leonardo da Vinci. The Mona Lisa."
列奥纳多・达・芬奇，蒙娜丽莎
Professor, the Mona Lisa is right over here.
教授，“蒙娜丽莎”就在这边
Look at this. He must have thrown it from the window.
看这个，他一定把这个扔出了窗口
Smart to hit the truck.
很聪明，扔到卡车上
What, you admire him now?
怎么，崇拜他了？
We're stupid. Who did we leave at the museum?
我们真笨，我们把谁留在博物馆了？
Ledoux? Get him on the radio!
勒杜斯？让他通话
Her smile is in the lower spatial frequencies.
她的微笑呈现一种低频空间震荡
The horizon is significantly lower on the left than it is on the right.
左面的地平线明显比右面的低
Why?
为什么？
Well, see, she appears larger from the left than on the right.
看，这样她从左面看起来 要比从右面看上去大
Historically, the left was female, the right was male.
历史上，左面代表阴性，右面代表阳性
The sacred feminine.
女神
Why do you say that?
你干嘛这么说？
Something Sauniere said the first time we came here.
我们第一次来这的时候索尼埃提起的
There. Blood.
看那，血迹
Hey.
嘿
"So dark the con of man."
男人的欺骗是如此黑暗
No. It doesn't say that.
不，不是这个意思
Is it another anagram? Can you break it?
又是一条乱序字谜？ 你能猜到吗？
Professor, hurry. Hurry!
教授，快点！
Moon. Sermon. Charms.
月亮(moon)，布道(sermon) 魅力(charm)
Demons. Omens. Codes. Monks. Ranks. Rocks.
恶魔，预兆，密码 僧侣，等级，岩石
Madonna of the Rocks.
《岩间圣母》
Da Vinci.
达・芬奇
Careful. Careful.
小心，小心
This can't be this. The fleur-de-lis.
这不可能，鸢尾花徽
Stay where you are!
待那别动！
Let go of the painting...
放下那画
...and put it on the ground.
放到地上
No. You put your gun down.
不，你把枪放下
Now!
马上
Or else I will destroy the painting.
不然我就毁了这画
Hurry up!
快点！
Slide your gun to me.
把你的枪踢给我
Be careful.
小心点
I never really liked this painting.
我从来都不喜欢这画
Run.
快跑
It was Sauniere's.
是索尼埃的
I remember finding it once when I was a girl.
我记得我小时候找到过它一次
He'd promised he'd give it to me one day.
他保证过他有天会给我的
Have you ever heard those words before, Sophie?
你以前听说过那些话吗，索菲
"So dark the con of man"?
男人的欺骗是如此黑暗
No. Have you?
没有过，你听过？
When you were a child, were you aware of any secret gatherings?
你小的时候，见过什么秘密集会吗？
Anything ritualistic in nature?
任何仪式？
Meetings your grandfather would've wanted kept secret?
某个集会你祖父希望不为人知？
Was there ever any talk of something called the Priory of Sion?
有没有听过一个叫做 郇山隐修会的组织
The what? Why are you asking these things?
什么？你干嘛问这些东西？
The Priory of Sion is a myth.
郇山隐修会是一个传说
One of the world's oldest and most secret societies, with leaders like...
一个世界上最古老最神秘的组织 它的领袖包括
...Sir Isaac Newton, da Vinci himself.
伊萨克・牛顿爵士 和达・芬奇本人
The fleur-de-lis is their crest.
鸢尾花是他们的标志
They're guardians of a secret they supposedly refer to...
他们守护着一个秘密 他们称之为
...as "the dark con of man."
男人的欺骗是如此黑暗
But what secret?
什么秘密
The Priory of Sion protects the source of God's power on earth.
郇山隐修会保护着 上帝在世间的力量来源
I can't do this by myself.
靠我自己完不成这事
I'm in enough trouble as it is. That's my embassy.
但我的麻烦已经够多了 那是我的大使馆
Please.
求你了
Even if we could get out of this...
即使我们能摆脱这些
Okay.
好
No, no, no. You're not gonna make it. You're not gonna make it!
不，不，你办不到的 你办不到的
Well, that was...
哇，那真是...
We won't last long in this car.
我们不能在这车里待太久
Fache doesn't like to be eluded, even on a good day.
法希不喜欢罪犯逃跑 即使天好也不行
We need to get out of sight.
我们得躲开别人的视线
Christ, give me strength.
基督啊，赐予我力量
You are a ghost.
你是个鬼魂
Stealing in a house of God!
在上帝的房内偷窃
You are an angel.
你是个天使
Christ, give me strength.
基督啊，赐予我力量
You have powerful friends.
您的朋友位高权重
Bishop Aringarosa has been kind to me.
阿林加洛沙主教对我很好
I could not miss this chance to pray inside the Saint-Sulpice.
我不能错过在圣苏比教堂祈祷的机会
A pity you couldn't wait for morning.
很遗憾您不能等到天明
The light is not ideal.
光线不是很好
Tell me, Sister, please, of the Rose Line.
请告诉我，嬷嬷，玫瑰线是什么
A rose line is any line that goes from the North to South Poles.
玫瑰线是任何一条从北极到南极的线 （又称子午线）
Set into the streets of Paris, 135 brass markers...
巴黎的街道上，有135处铜标记
...mark the world's first prime meridian...
他们标出了世界上第一条本初子午线
...which passed through this very church.
而该线正好经过本教堂
It hides beneath the Rose.
藏于玫瑰线下
I'm sorry?
您说什么？
Sister.
嬷嬷
I do not want to keep you. I will show myself out.
我不想耽误您的时间 我会自己找路出去的
I insist.
我坚持
May the peace of the Lord be with you.
愿主的祥和与您同在
And with you.
与您也同在
Gray Smart Car. Black roof.
发现一辆灰色的城市精灵车，黑顶
Corner of Denain Boulevard at the train station.
在德南大道的角落，火车站旁边
How could you let them get away?
你怎么能让他们逃跑？
Why not just shoot the damn painting? Lmbecile!
干嘛不射穿那幅破画？蠢货
You should put his cigar out in your hand!
真该把他的雪茄在你手上捅灭
Get out of here!
滚出去
They found Neveu's car abandoned at the train station.
他们发现奈芙的车了 被扔在火车站
And two tickets to Brussels paid for with Langdors credit card.
还有两张去布鲁塞尔的车票 是用兰登的信用卡付的
A decoy, I'm sure.
诱饵，我肯定
All the same, send an officer to the station.
老方法，派一个警官去车站
Question all the taxi drivers. I'll put this on the wire.
询问所有的出租车司机 我把这个放到网上
Interpol? We're not sure he's guilty.
国际刑警？我们还不肯定他是否有罪
I know he's guilty. Beyond a doubt.
我知道他有罪，毫无疑问
Robert Langdon is guilty.
罗伯特・兰登有罪
This is the Bois de Boulogne?
这是布劳涅森林？
We should be safe in this park for a few minutes.
我们在这公园里待几分钟 应该是安全的
Your police don't patrol this park.
你们警察竟然不在这公园巡逻
Stay here.
待在这里
Police.
警察
What do you want?
你要什么？
Fifty euros for all your stuff.
五十欧元换你所有的东西
Go and get something to eat.
去找点东西吃
Did it occur to you that could be dangerous?
你没觉得那可能很危险吗？
No. And now we have a place to think.
不，现在我们有了个可以思考的地方
Any ideas, professor?
有什么想法吗，教授
You could've just handed me a piece of a UFO from Area 51.
你给我的说不定是 51区的一块飞碟残骸
"What's the next step?"
“下一步是什么”
With him, it's always:
他总是这么说
"Sophie, what's the next step?"
“索菲，下一步是什么”
Puzzles.
谜语
Codes.
密码
A treasure hunt.
是寻宝啊
To find his killer.
要找到杀他的凶手
Maybe there is something about this Priory of Sion.
说不定郇山隐修会 会有关系
I hope not.
希望不要
Any Priory story ends in bloodshed. They were butchered by the Church.
任何隐修会的故事的结局都是流血 他们是被教会屠杀的
It all started over a thousand years ago when a French king...
这一切开始于一千年前
...conquered the holy city of Jerusalem.
一位法国国王占领了圣城耶路撒冷
This crusade, one of the most massive and sweeping in history...
这次十字军东征是历史上最大规模的一次
...was actually orchestrated by a secret brotherhood...
但实际上它是由一个秘密兄弟会组织的
...the Priory of Sion...
就是郇山隐修会
...and their military arm, the Knights Templar.
还有他们的军事组织，圣殿骑士团
But the Templars were created to protect the Holy Land.
但圣殿骑士是用来保卫圣地的啊
That was a cover to hide their true goal, according to this myth.
根据这个传说，那只不过是伪装 用来隐藏真实目的
Supposedly the invasion was to find an artifact...
据说这次进攻是为了寻找一样圣物
...lost since the time of Christ.
从基督时代就丢失的圣物
An artifact, it was said, the Church would kill to possess.
据说为占有这件圣物，教会将不吝杀戮
Did they find it, this buried treasure?
他们找到了吗，这件埋没的财宝
Put it this way:
这么说吧
One day the Templars simply stopped searching.
有天圣殿骑士停止了搜寻
They quit the Holy Land and traveled directly to Rome.
他们退出了圣地，直奔罗马
Whether they blackmailed the papacy...
不知道是他们敲诈了教皇
...or the Church bought their silence, no one knows.
还是教会想收买他们，无人知晓
But it is a fact the papacy declared these Priory knights...
但最终事实是教皇宣布这些修会骑士们
...these Knights Templar, of limitless power.
这些圣殿骑士们有无限的权力
By the 1300s, the Templars had grown too powerful.
到了14世纪初，圣殿骑士们 已经变得过于强大
Too threatening.
过于有威胁
So the Vatican issued secret orders...
以至于梵蒂冈下达了秘密指令
...to be opened simultaneously all across Europe.
该指令要全欧同时开启
The Pope had declared the Knights Templar Satan worshipers...
教皇宣布圣殿骑士们搞恶魔崇拜
...and said God had charged him with cleansing the earth of these heretics.
说上帝责令他清除世间这些异端
The plan went off like clockwork.
这一计划执行的像时钟一样准确
The Templars were all but exterminated.
圣殿骑士们几乎被屠杀光了
The date was October 13th, 1307. A Friday.
那天是1307年10月13日，星期五
Friday the 13th.
黑色星期五
The Pope sent troops to claim the Priory's treasure...
教皇派军队去接收修会的财产
...but they found nothing.
但一无所获
The few surviving Knights of the Priory had vanished...
幸存的几个修会骑士失踪了
...and the search for their sacred artifact began again.
对他们圣物的搜寻则重新开始
What artifact? I've never heard about any of this.
什么圣物？我从来没听说过这些
Yes, you have.
你听说过的
Almost everyone on earth has.
地球人差不多都知道
You just know it as the Holy Grail.
只是在你的认知中它被称为圣杯
Please, Sauniere thought he knew the location of the Holy Grail?
拜托，索尼埃觉得自己知道圣杯的位置？
Maybe more than that.
可能还不仅仅如此
This cross and the flower, this could be very old. But look.
这个十字架和花，可能年代很悠久，看
This metal here underneath is much newer, and there's a modern ID stamp.
这下面的这块金属年头很新 这还有个现代的身份标志
"Haxo 24."
“豪克斯 24”
And these dots. These dots are read by a laser.
还有这些点，是用激光来读的
This is more than a pendant. This is a key your grandfather left you.
这不仅仅是个挂件 这是你祖父留给你的一把钥匙
He left us, professor.
他留给我们的，教授
And vingt-quatre Haxo, it's not an ID stamp.
而“豪克斯街24号”，这不是什么身份标志
It's a street address.
这是街道地址
This is Jacques Sauniere.
我是雅克・索尼埃
Please leave a message after the tone.
请在嘟一声后留言
Please, Monsieur Sauniere, pick up the phone.
拜托，索尼埃先生，请接电话
This is Sandrine Bieil.
我是桑德琳・比耶尔
I have called the list.
我已经给名单上的人打了电话
I fear the other guardians are dead.
我担心其他守护者都已经死去了
The lie has been told.
那个谎言已经出现
The floor panel has been broken.
地板也被撬开了
Please, monsieur, pick up the phone. I beg you.
求你了，先生，快接电话
Job 38, verse 11.
约伯记38章11节
Do you know it, Sister?
你知道那个吗，嬷嬷？
Hitherto shalt thou come...
“你将到此”
...but no further.
“但到此为止”
"But no further."
“到此为止”
Do you mock me?
你在挖苦我吗？
Where is the keystone?
拱心石在哪里？
I do not know.
我不知道
No.
不
You are a sister of the Church...
你是教会的嬷嬷
...and yet you serve them: The Priory.
而你却在为他们服务：隐修会
Jesus had but one true message. That...
耶稣只传达了一个旨意，那...
Come, you saints of God.
来吧，主前的圣人
Hasten, angels of the Lord.
快来，侍奉主的天使
To receive her soul.
接收她的灵魂
And bring her to the sight of the Almighty.
带她到那万能的主的眼前
In the name of the Father, the Son, and the Holy Spirit.
以圣父，圣子，和圣灵的名义
Welcome, bishop.
欢迎啊，主教大人
May Christ be with you.
愿基督与你同在
And also with you.
也与你同在
It's been too long, Manuel.
很久没见了，曼努埃尔
I saw your press conference.
我看了你的新闻发布会了
Very priestly.
非常神圣
Vultures.
一帮秃鹫
But you need a good cover to fly into Italy these days.
但是这年头得有个好借口才能飞去意大利
So how are things in Rome?
罗马情况如何？
We serve at his pleasure.
我们为他服务
Today is today.
今天只有一个
But there are many tomorrows.
但明天却无穷无尽
Vatican cellars.
梵蒂冈窖藏
1976.
1976年份的
Seventy-six, a year of independence. How fitting.
76年，独立之年啊，真合适
I thought you'd like it.
我还以为你会喜欢它
I'll fetch the others.
我去接其他人
Welcome, bishop.
欢迎，主教
This council is convened.
委员会已经被召集了
Our words shall never pass these walls.
我们说的话绝不能外传
What business, say you?
您有什么事情？
As you know, my request for funds...
如各位所知，我要求一笔基金
Yes, 20 million euro in untraceable bearer bonds.
是的，两千万欧元的 无法追查的不记名债券
A tad more than petty cash. Wouldrt you say, bishop?
比卑微的现钞还要难一些啊 您不觉得吗，主教？
The endeavor is complex. Freedom has a high cost.
我们付出的心力也很多 自由可不便宜
And, of course, you will deliver us.
不过，你一定会给我们自由的
How fortunate we are.
我们还真是幸运啊
I only offer a route to the renewal of faith for all men.
我只提供一条路，能恢复所有人的信仰
How humble.
好谦卑啊
Our savior, Bishop Aringarosa.
我们的救世主，阿林加洛沙主教
Were we to grant your request...
如果我们批准你的请求
...when would this mission commence?
这计划什么时候可以执行？
- Actually, tonight. - What?
- 事实上，今晚 - 什么？
- It has begun. - We have not agreed.
- 它已经开始了 - 我们还没同意
How dare you presume to...
你怎么敢假定...
I do not presume, I act!
我没有假定，我行动
The Vaticars unwillingness to support us...
梵蒂冈不愿支持我们
...is both impious and cowardly.
是不敬和懦弱的表现
Blood is being spilled because true Christian values lie in ruins. No more!
有流血是因为基督教的真正价值 是建立在废墟上的，没其他好说的
This council has forgotten its very purpose.
本委员会已经忘记了自己的根本宗旨
Tonight...
今晚
...the Grail will be destroyed.
圣杯将被摧毁
The Priory's few remaining members will be silenced.
隐修会的余党将被清除
I was contacted by a man who calls himself only "the Teacher."
有个自称为“导师”的男人联系过我
He knows a great deal about this council.
他对本委员会了解很多
And about the Priory.
对隐修会了解也不少
Two prostitutes identified Langdon and Neveu...
两个妓女指认出兰登和奈芙
...getting into a taxi in the Bois de Boulogne.
乘出租车进了布劳涅森林
Because of your expertise?
是因为你的专长吗？
- I'm sorry? - About the Priory.
- 什么意思 - 关于隐修会
Do you think that's why Sauniere sought you out?
你觉得索尼埃是因此才找你的吗？
I can think of dozens of scholars who know a lot more about it.
我能想到数十位学者对此了解的更多
Actually, I didn't think he liked me very much.
事实上，我不觉得他很喜欢我
Once made a joke at my expense. Got a big laugh out of it.
他曾经开了个我的玩笑 引得哄堂大笑
What was it?
是什么？
How may I help you?
我能帮您做什么？
The door to the right, please.
请去右面那扇门
That was quite a performance.
刚才演的可真不错
The little shit should know better than to play politics with me.
那小子和我玩政治还不够格
I know I got in front of you, old friend.
我知道我没事先征求你的同意，老朋友
I did what I thought was best.
我只是执行了我能想到的最佳方案
So...
那
...now what?
现在做什么？
Now we wait for the Teacher's call.
现在我们等“导师”的电话
Good evening. I am Andre Vernet, the night manager.
晚上好，我是安德烈・韦尔内 夜间值班经理
I take it this is your first visit to our establishment?
我想这是您第一次来我们这里吧
Yes.
是的
Understood.
可以理解
Keys are often passed on and first-time users...
钥匙经常被继承，而第一次来的用户
...are sometimes uncertain of protocol.
有时对程序不太了解
Keys are essentially numbered Swiss accounts.
钥匙本质上就是瑞士银行帐号
Often willed through generations.
通常会被继承很多代
Is it yours, mademoiselle?
这是您的吗，小姐？
The shortest safety-deposit-box lease is 50 years.
保险箱最短的租约是50年
And what's your longest account?
你们时间最长的帐户呢？
Quite a bit longer.
非常悠久
Technologies change, keys are updated.
科技改变，钥匙也会被更新
But our accounts date back to the beginning of banking itself.
但我们的帐户可以上溯到 银行业初始之时
Once the computer confirms your key...
一旦计算机确认了钥匙
...enter your account number and your box is retrieved.
请输入您的帐户号码 你的箱子就将被拿到
The room is yours, as long as you like.
这间房您想用多久都可以
What if I lost track of my account number?
如果我丢了我帐户的号码怎么办？
How might I recover it?
我怎样恢复呢？
I'm afraid each key is paired with a 10-digit number...
每把钥匙对应一个10位数的号码
...known only to the account bearer.
只有帐户所有人才知道
I hope you manage to remember it.
我希望你能想法记起来
A single wrong entry disables the system.
一次错误输入就会让整个系统失效
- Ten.
- 10位
Your grandfather's Fibonacci sequence.
你祖父的斐波那契数列
Scrambled, unscrambled?
乱序的，还是顺序的？
Unscrambled.
顺序的
It's your key.
插钥匙进去
Funny, I don't even like history.
很有趣，我甚至都不喜欢历史
I've never seen much good come from looking to the past.
我很少见到回顾历史 能有什么好的收获
Moment of truth.
揭晓真相的时刻到了
My God. I don't believe this.
上帝啊，我真难以相信
A rose.
玫瑰花标
The rose was a symbol for the Holy Grail.
玫瑰是圣杯的标志
Forgive the intrusion.
请原谅我的打扰
I'm afraid the police arrived more quickly than I anticipated.
好像警察来的比我料想的还要快
You must follow me, please.
请跟我来
For your own safety.
这是为了你们的安全
You knew they were coming?
你知道他们会来？
My guard alerted me to your status when you arrived.
你们来时警卫提醒过我你们的情况
Yours is one of our oldest and highest-level accounts.
你们持有的是我们 最古老最高级的帐户之一
It includes a safe-passage clause.
包括一个安全通行条款
Safe passage?
安全通行
If you would step inside, please. Time is of the essence.
请进去，时间是关键
In there?
进那里？
Hey, is there a problem?
嘿，有什么问题吗？
Good evening, sir. Police.
晚上好，先生，警察办公
I just drive from here to Zurich. Not French, English?
我刚从苏黎世来，不会法语 英语行吗？
- English? - Yes.
- 英语？ - 是的
We are looking for two criminals.
我们在找两名罪犯
You came to the right place. They're all criminals here.
你来对地方了 这里什么罪犯都有
Would you mind opening the hold?
你介意打开让我们搜查一下吗？
Please. You think they trust us, the wages I get paid?
拜托，就凭我拿的这点工资 你觉得他们能信任我？
You don't have keys to your own truck?
你自己开的卡车，自己没有钥匙？
It's armored. Keys get sent to the destination.
是装甲车，钥匙直接送到终点
You mind? I'm on a schedule here.
你介意吗？我要赶时间
And do all the drivers wear a Rolex?
所有的司机都带劳力士吗？
What?
什么？
This piece of shit.
这破玩意啊
Forty euros in Barbes.
在巴拜斯40欧元就能买到
Yours for 35.
卖你35如何
No, no, no.
不，不用了
- Thirty. - No. It's okay, it's okay.
- 30 - 不，没关系，不用了
Come on, 30, eh?
别这样嘛，才30
I said, no!
我说了不要
Move along!
走吧
Now we wait.
现在我们等待
The Teacher will call and tell me where to deliver the money.
“导师”会打电话来 告诉我们把钱送哪
You have put tremendous faith in this Teacher of yours.
你对这个“导师”真是非常信任啊
Yes, I have. And I have given him an angel to do his will.
是的，我还给了他一个天使来达成他的意愿
For surely there is no better soldier for God than my Silas.
毫无疑问，没人比我的塞拉斯 更适合做上帝的斗士了
I firmly resolve, with the help of thy grace, to confess my sins...
我诚挚决定，在上帝的帮助下 忏悔我的罪行
...to do penance and to amend my life.
接受苦修，改过自新
Amen.
阿门
I chastise my body.
我鞭打我的身体
The Holy Grail.
圣杯
A magic cup. The source of God's power on earth.
神奇的杯子 上帝在世间力量的来源
It's nonsense.
都是胡扯
You don't believe in God.
你不相信上帝
No.
不
I don't believe in some magic from the sky.
我不相信上天降下的什么魔力
Just people.
只信人
Sometimes that they can be kind.
有时他们很善良
And that's enough?
这就够了？
Well, I think it has to be. I think it's all we have.
我觉得是吧，我觉得这就是全部了
Are you a God-fearing man, professor?
你是个害怕上帝的人吗，教授？
I was raised a Catholic.
我在天主教家庭中长大
Well, that's not really an answer.
这可不算答案
Professor, are you okay?
教授，你还好吗？
Go ahead, open it.
动手，打开吧
Go on.
动手
A cryptex.
一个密码筒
They are used to keep secrets.
他们是用来保守秘密的
It's da Vinci's design.
是达・芬奇的设计
You write the information on a papyrus scroll...
你在草纸上写下一些信息
...which is then rolled around a thin glass vial of vinegar.
把纸绕在一个装满醋的玻璃小瓶周围
If you force it open, the vial breaks...
如果你用暴力打开，瓶子会破
...vinegar dissolves papyrus...
醋就会把草纸腐蚀掉
...and your secret is lost forever.
你的秘密也就永远丢失了
The only way to access the information...
唯一获取这些信息的方法
...is to spell out the password...
就是拼出密码
...with these five dials, each with 26 letters.
密码由五圈组成，每圈有26个字母
That's 12 million possibilities.
总共有超过一千二百万种可能
I've never met a girl who knew that much about a cryptex.
我从来没碰到过一个女孩 有这么了解密码筒
Sauniere made one for me once.
索尼埃曾经为我做了一个
My grandfather gave me a wagon.
我祖父给我了一辆大众
This clearly is not the Holy Grail.
这肯定不是圣杯
Come on.
加油
Please, you're not all right.
怎么了，你不太对劲
May I try something?
我可以试试吗？
I don't know why it works.
我不知道那为什么奏效
My mother used to do it when I was scared, I think.
小时妈妈曾经用这个 来安抚我的恐惧，我觉得
You think?
你觉得？
Yes.
是的
Feeling better, Sophie?
觉得好点吗，索菲？
My parents died in a car crash with my brother.
我父母和我兄弟死于一场车祸
I was 4.
那时我只有4岁
I'm sorry.
对不起
It was many years ago.
那是很多年前了
Better?
好点吗？
Yeah.
是的
Okay.
那好
Twenty years waiting for someone to come for that box...
等人来拿那个箱子等了20年
...and now it's you two murderers. Bring it to me.
结果来的是两个凶手，拿过来
I don't know what you're talking about.
我不知道你在说什么
All right! Okay!
好啦，给你
Right now!
就现在
Step back!
后退
No one will lose sleep over a couple on a killing spree.
在杀戮狂欢中没人会担心一对夫妇的
Turn around.
转过去
You too, mademoiselle.
你也是，小姐
Sophie!
索菲
Get in the truck!
进卡车里去
I'll drive! Hurry!
我来开，快点
- Better? - Always, if I got too nervous...
- 好点吗？ - 总是这样，如果我太紧张
...I had to put my head out of the window not to be sick.
我就得把头伸出去，才不会恶心
Sauniere used to say I was like a dog.
索尼埃总是说我像狗
A cute dog. You know, a little dog.
可爱的狗，小小狗
What happened between you and your grandfather, Sophie?
你和你祖父之间到底发生了什么？
I've jammed my shoulder, I've been shot at, I'm bleeding.
我夹伤了肩膀，被人家用枪打 我在流血
I need to know.
我要知道
You say he raised you, but you two don't talk anymore.
你说他把你养大的 但你们两个没再交谈过
You call him by his last name.
你用姓来称呼他
You say you hate history.
你说你恨历史
Nobody hates history. They hate their own histories.
没人会恨历史，人们只会恨自己的过去
So now you're a psychologist too?
现在你又成了心理医生了？
What if Sauniere had started to groom you for the Priory?
说不定索尼埃是在为你进隐修会准备呢
What do you mean, groom me?
什么意思，准备？
Your grandfather gave you puzzles and cryptex as a child.
在你小时你祖父给你谜语和密码筒
Say Sauniere was hoping one day you would join him in the Priory.
比如说索尼埃希望有天 你也会加入到他的隐修会当中
Still, years later, when he imagines...
于是，多年以后，当他觉得
...the Grail is in danger, he reaches out to you.
圣杯有了危险，他就找了你
So you are saying all this is real? The Priory, the Holy Grail?
你是说这些都是真的了？ 隐修会，圣杯？
We've been dragged into a world of people who think this stuff is real.
我们被扯进对此信以为真的人群里了
- Real enough to kill for. - Who?
- 真到可以为此杀人 - 是谁？
I'm out of my field here.
这就不是我熟悉的了
I do know a Grail historian, absolutely obsessed with Priory myth.
我倒是认识一个圣杯历史学家 对于隐修会的传说绝对着迷
An Englishman, lives here in France.
一个住在法国的英国人
Do you trust this man?
你信任这个人吗？
I hope you can.
我希望你可以
Vernet, Andre.
安德烈・韦尔内
It seems you're not a driver at all.
看起来你根本不是什么司机嘛
Apparently, you lost your tongue along with your truck.
看来你车丢了，连话业不会说了
Aiding and abetting two murder suspects.
帮助和怂恿两个杀人嫌犯
That carries jail time.
这足够进监狱了
Speak to my lawyer.
和我律师去谈吧
All this confusion, violence, vanishing property...
这么多混乱，暴力，失踪的财富
It might get around that your bank is less than ideal, don't you think?
看来你的银行也不是那么完美嘛，对吧？
You think you're in pain now, Andre Vernet?
你觉得现在你很痛苦了吗 安德烈・韦尔内
My cause is won'th your life. Understand?
你的罪行足够判无期徒刑，懂吗？
What do you want?
你想要什么？
Your truck carries a homing device. Activate it.
你的车装有制导装D，启动它
Please wait. I'll see if he's available.
请等等，我看看他有没有空
It's on the wrong side.
这装错边了
Leigh likes all things to be English, including his cars.
雷喜欢把所有东西弄成英国式的 包括他的车
Robert! Do I owe you money?
罗伯特，我欠你钱吗？
Leigh, my friend...
雷，我的朋友
...care to open up for an old colleague?
可以开门让老同事进来吗？
- Of course. - Thank you.
- 当然 - 谢谢
But first, a test of honor.
但先要来个正直测试
Three questions.
三个问题
Fire away.
说吧
Your first:
第一个
Shall I serve coffee or tea?
我该上咖啡还是茶？
Tea, of course.
当然是茶
Excellent.
很好
Second: Milk or lemon?
第二个：加牛奶还是柠檬？
Milk?
牛奶？
That would depend on the tea.
那要看是什么茶
Correct.
正确
And now the third and most grave of inquiries:
现在是第三个也是最难回答的
In which year did a Harvard sculler outrow an Oxford man at Henley?
哪一年哈佛的赛艇选手 在亨利赛道上赢了牛津的选手？
Surely such a travesty has never occurred.
这种滑稽的事情肯定没发生过
Your heart is true.
你有一颗真诚的心
You may pass.
你可以通过了
Welcome to Chateau Villette.
欢迎来到维莱特堡
Leigh Teabing has spent his entire life...
雷・提彬花费了一生的时间
...studying the Grail. That thing is one hot tamale.
研究圣杯，那东西简直就像 热辣的玉米粉蒸肉
Sorry?
对不起？
The cryptex, it's a hot coal.
密码筒，让人心热的像热炭团
A hot potato?
热土豆？懂吗？
So you want to keep our chest close to our cards, yes?
看来你总是想让人提心吊胆啊
Very close.
没错
The truck's signal is coming online.
卡车的信号出现了
It's about time.
时候到了
Locked on and tracking, sir.
锁定，开始追踪，长官
Very good. Tell Collet not to move in until I get there.
维莱特，很好，让科莱 在我到达前不要行动
Attention! All of Collet's units to Chateau Villette.
注意，科莱小组全部成员 出发去维莱特堡
The suspects Neveu and Langdon are likely at that location.
嫌犯奈芙和兰登很可能在那里
Aringarosa.
阿林加洛沙
I still don't know why he put you into this...
我还是不知道他为什么把你扯进来
...and I'm sorry.
我很抱歉
But...
但是
...l'm also very glad.
我也很高兴
You are requested to make yourself at home.
就把这当成您家里
Robert!
罗伯特
And you travel with a maiden, it seems.
看起来你旅行还带女佣啊
Sir Leigh Teabing, may I present Miss Sophie Neveu.
雷・提彬爵士，请容许我 介绍索菲・奈芙小姐
Sophie, Sir Leigh Teabing.
索菲，这位是雷・提彬爵士
It's an honor to welcome you...
很荣幸欢迎您
...even though it's late.
即使是这么晚
Thank you for having us. I realize it's quite late.
谢谢你接待我们 我意识到现在确实很晚了
So late, mademoiselle, it's almost early.
是太晚了，小姐，都快早上了
What a lovely smile you have.
你的笑容多可爱啊
Earl Grey?
格雷伯爵茶？
Lemon.
加柠檬
Correct.
正确
Chateau Villette. Yes.
维莱特堡，好的
- No. - Oh, you must.
- 不 - 哦，你一定要
Remy is from Lyons, but nevertheless...
雷米是从里昂来的，但
...he is fantastic with sauces.
他的酱调的真不错
- Thank you. - No, I can't.
- 谢谢 - 不，我不行
A dramatic late-night arrival.
深夜的戏剧性来访
Mention of life and death.
还事关生死
What can an old cripple do for you, Robert?
一个老瘸子能帮你做什么呢？罗伯特
We wanna talk about the Priory of Sion.
我们想谈谈郇山隐修会
The keepers?
保管者？
The secret war?
秘密战争？
Sorry for all the mystery.
很抱歉这么神神秘秘的
Leigh, I'm into something here that I cannot understand.
雷，我碰到一些我无法理解的东西
You?
你？
- Really? - Not without your help.
- 真的？ - 没有你的帮助就无法理解
Playing to my vanity, Robert. You should be ashamed.
把我抛在一边，罗伯特 你该感到羞耻
Not if it works.
有效就无所谓
There are always four:
它总是由4人组成
The Grand Master and the three senechaux...
一位大师和三位长老
...make up the primary guardians of the Grail.
他们是圣杯的主要守护人
Thank you, Remy. That'll be all for now.
谢谢，雷米，没你的事了
The Priory's members span our very globe itself.
隐修会的成员遍及我们这个星球
Philippe de Cherisey exposed that as a hoax in 1967.
菲利普・德・谢瑞希 在1967年发现这是个谎言
And that is what they want you to believe.
这就是他们希望你相信的
The Priory is charged with a single task:
隐修会只有一项任务
To protect the greatest secret in modern history.
保护现代历史上最大的秘密
The source of God's power on earth.
上帝在世间的力量来源
No, that's a common misunderstanding.
不，那是个普遍的误解
The Priory protects the source of the Church's power on earth:
隐修会保护的是教会在世间力量的来源
The Holy Grail.
圣杯
I don't understand.
我不懂
What power? Some magic dishes?
什么样的力量，比如魔法尘吗？
Robert. Has he been telling you that the Holy Grail is a cup?
罗伯特，他是不是告诉你圣杯是个杯子？
To understand the Holy Grail, my dear...
要理解圣杯，亲爱的
...you must first understand the Holy Bible.
你首先要理解圣经
The Good Book did not arrive by facsimile from heaven.
圣经不是天堂给我们传真过来的
The Bible as we know it was finally presided over by one man:
如我们所知的 圣经最终是由一个人主持修订的
The pagan emperor Constantine.
异教徒皇帝康斯坦丁
I thought Constantine was a Christian.
我以为康斯坦丁是基督徒
Oh, hardly, no. He was a lifelong pagan...
哦，不，他一辈子都是异教徒
...who was baptized on his deathbed.
是在尸床上受的洗礼
Constantine was Rome's supreme holy man.
康斯坦丁是罗马的超级圣人
From time immemorial...
从远古开始
...his people had worshiped a balance between nature's male deities...
他的族人就一直在崇拜一种平衡
...and the goddess, or sacred feminine.
自然界的神和女神间的平衡
But a growing religious turmoil was gripping Rome.
但愈演愈烈的宗教纷争控制了罗马
Three centuries earlier...
三个世纪前
...a young Jew named Jesus had come along...
出现了一位年轻的叫耶稣的犹太人
...preaching love and a single God.
他鼓吹爱和一神论
Centuries after his crucifixion...
他被钉十字架数个世纪之后
...Christ's followers had grown exponentially...
耶稣的信徒数目成倍的增加
...and had started a religious war against the pagans.
挑起了一场与异教徒间的宗教战争
Or did the pagans commence war against the Christians?
也许是异教徒对基督徒宣的战呢？
Leigh, we can't be sure who began the atrocities in that period.
雷，我们无法确认在那时 暴行由哪方开始
We can at least agree that the conflict grew to such proportions...
但我们起码可以认同 这次争端的规模之大
...that it threatened to tear Rome in two.
以至于它可能将罗马一分为二
So Constantine may have been a lifelong pagan...
而康斯坦丁也许是终身的异教徒
...but he was also a pragmatist.
但他也是一位实用主义者
And in 325 anno Domini...
在公元325年
...he decided to unify Rome under a single religion, Christianity.
他决定将罗马统一在 一个宗教之下，基督教
Christianity was on the rise. He didn't want his empire torn apart.
基督教正在壮大 他当然不想让他的帝国分崩离析
And to strengthen this new Christian tradition...
为了加强这个新基督教传统
...Constantine held a famous ecumenical gathering...
康斯坦丁举行了一次著名的 基督教全教会大会
...known as the Council of Nicaea.
被称为尼西亚会议
And at this council...
在这次会议上
...the many sects of Christianity debated and voted on, well...
很多基督教派别进行了争论和投票
...everything, from the acceptance and rejection of specific gospels...
范围包括一切事务 从接受还是抵制某个福音书
...to the date for Easter...
到复活节的日期
...to the administering of the sacraments, and of course...
到圣餐的管理，当然
...the immortality of Jesus.
也包括耶稣的神性
I don't follow.
我没懂
Well, ma chere, until that moment in history...
亲爱的，在这个历史时刻之前
...Jesus was viewed by many of his followers as a mighty prophet...
耶稣被他的很多信徒 看作是伟大的先知
...as a great and powerful man, but a man nevertheless.
伟大的，强大的人，但毕竟还是个人
A mortal man.
一个凡人
Some Christians held that Jesus was mortal.
某些基督徒坚持耶稣是凡人
Some Christians believed he was divine.
某些基督徒则认为他是神
Not the Son of God?
不是上帝之子？
Not even his nephew twice removed.
连他的侄孙都算不上
Hold on, you're saying Jesus' divinity came from a vote.
等等，你说耶稣的神性是投票投出来的
Well, remember, in those days, gods were everywhere.
而且，记住在那些日子里 神可遍地都是
By infusing Jesus the man with the divine magic...
给凡人耶稣灌注神秘
...by making him capable of earthly miracles...
称他可以创造世间的奇迹
...as well as his own resurrection, Constantine turned him into a god...
再加上他自己的复活 康斯坦丁把他变成了一位神
...but within the human world.
不过这也仅仅是在人类社会里
And he basically knocked the more distant gods out of the game.
然后他就把其他没什么关系的神 全踢一边去了
Constantine did not create Jesus' divinity.
康斯坦丁没有创造出耶稣的神性
He simply sanctioned an already widely held idea.
他只不过批准了一个 被广泛接受的意见
- Semantics. - No, it's not semantics.
- 文字游戏 - 不，不是文字游戏
You're interpreting facts to support your own conclusions.
你把事实按自己的想法理解 用来支持你的结论
Fact: For many Christians, Jesus was mortal one day and divine the next.
事实是：对很多基督徒来说 耶稣今天是凡人明天又是神
For some Christians, his divinity was enanced.
对某些基督徒来说 他的神性只是增强了
Absurd. There was a formal announcement of his promotion.
荒谬，对于这种提升有正式的公告的
They couldn't even agree on the Nicene Creed!
他们甚至在尼西亚会议上都无法统一
Excuse me. "Who is God, who is man?"
对不起，“谁是神，谁是人啊”
How many have been murdered over this question?
有多少人因为这个问题被谋杀了
As long as there has been a one true God...
只要还存在着唯一的真神
...there has been killing in his name.
就会有以他的名义进行的杀戮
Now let me show you the Grail.
现在我来给你展示一下圣杯
This used to be the ballroom.
这曾经是舞厅
I have little occasion to dance these days.
不过现在我没什么机会跳舞了
I trust you recognize The Last Supper...
我相信你一定认得《最后的晚餐》
...the great fresco by Leonardo da Vinci.
列奥纳多・达・芬奇的杰作
Now, my dear, if you would close your eyes.
现在，亲爱的，能不能合上你的眼睛
Oh, Leigh, save us the parlor tricks.
哦，雷，别玩你那套小把戏了
You asked for my help, I recall.
我记得是你来向我求助的
Allow an old man his indulgences.
就迁就一下一个老人嘛
Now, mademoiselle, where is Jesus sitting?
小姐，耶稣坐在哪？
- In the middle. - Good.
- 在中间 - 好
He and his disciples are breaking bread.
他和他的使徒们在分面包
And what drink?
喝的是什么呢？
Wine. They drank wine.
葡萄酒，他们喝葡萄酒
Splendid. And one final question:
好极了，最后一个问题
How many wineglasses are there on the table?
桌上有几个葡萄酒杯呢？
One? The Holy Grail?
一个？圣杯？
Open your eyes.
睁开眼吧
No single cup.
一个杯子都没有
No chalice.
没有圣餐杯
Well, that's a bit strange, isn't it?
这有点奇怪，对吧？
Considering both the Bible and standard Grail legend...
不管是圣经还是标准的圣杯传说
...celebrate this moment as the definitive arrival of the Holy Grail.
都把这个时刻作为圣杯的出现时刻来庆祝
Now, Robert, you could be of help to us.
现在，罗伯特，你可以帮帮我们了
If you'd be so kind as to show us the symbols for man and woman, please.
请你给我们展示一下 男人和女人的符号吧
No balloon animals. I can make a great duck.
没有充气玩具吗？我能装个不错的鸭子
This is the original icon for male. It's a rudimentary phallus.
这是最初的男性标志 未完全发育的阴茎
- Quite to the point. - Yes, indeed.
- 说到点子上了 - 是啊，没错
This is known as the blade.
这个符号被称作“刃形”
It represents aggression and manood.
它代表了进取心和男子气概
It's a symbol still used today in modern military uniforms.
这个符号今天仍然被现代军队制服采用
Yes, the more penises you have, the higher your rank. Boys will be boys.
是啊，你拥有的阴茎越多 级别就越高，男孩就是男孩
Now, as you would imagine, the female symbol is its exact opposite.
现在，你也该想到了吧 女性的标志刚好是反过来的
This is called the chalice.
这被称为“杯形”
And the chalice resembles a cup or vessel or, more importantly...
“杯形”像一个杯子，一个罐子 更重要的是
...the shape of a womars womb.
像女人子宫的形状
No, the Grail has never been a cup.
不，圣杯从来就不是一个杯子
It is quite literally this ancient symbol of womanood.
它在字面上指的就是 这个古老的女性标记
And in this case, a woman who carried a secret so powerful...
具体来说，它指的是 一个身怀绝世机密的女人
...that if revealed, it would devastate the very foundations of Christianity.
这个秘密一旦被揭露 基督教的根基就会被摧毁
Wait, please.
请等一下
You're saying the Holy Grail is a person? A woman?
你说圣杯是个人，一个女人？
And it turns out, she makes an appearance right there.
不仅如此，她还正好在那幅画上出现过
But they are all men.
但他们都是男人啊
Are they?
是吗？
What about that figure on the right hand of our Lord...
那位在主的右手边上的呢
...seated in the place of honor?
坐在尊位上的那位呢？
Flowing red hair.
柔顺的红发
Folded feminine hands.
叠起的女性双手
Hint of a bosom. No?
乳房若隐若现，对吧？
It's called scotoma. The mind sees what it chooses to see.
这就叫做盲点 想看见的才会被看见
Who is she?
她是谁？
My dear, that's Mary Magdalene.
亲爱的，那是抹大拉的玛丽
The prostitute?
那个妓女？
She was no such thing.
她从来不是妓女
Smeared by the Church in 591 anno Domini, poor dear.
那是教会在公元591年对她进行的侮蔑
Mary Magdalene was Jesus' wife.
抹大拉的玛丽是耶稣的妻子
This is an old wives' tale.
真是无稽之谈
The original one, in fact.
这才是原始的真相
There's virtually no empirical proof.
这基本没什么实证
He knows as well as I do there's much evidence to support it.
他和我都知道支持这个的证据有很多
Theories. There are theories.
理论，那些只是理论
Notice how Jesus and Mary are clothed.
注意看耶稣和玛丽的着装
Mirror images of each other.
彼此互为镜像
The mind sees what it chooses to see.
想看见的才会被看见
And venturing into the even more bizarre, notice how Jesus and Mary...
再看更奇怪的，注意耶稣和玛丽
...appear to be joined at the hip and are leaning away from each other...
他们的臀部是画在一起的 但上身彼此逐渐远离
...as if to create a shape in the negative space between them.
在两人之间形成了一个倒三角
Leonardo gives us the chalice.
列奥纳多给我们画了一个“杯形”
Yes. Oh, and Robert, notice what happens...
哦，还有，注意看如果
...when these two figures change position.
这两个人换一下位置
Just because da Vinci painted it doesn't make it true.
达・芬奇这么画的不代表 这就是真的啊
No. But history...
的确如此，但历史
...she does make it true.
历史上这就是真的
Now, listen to this. It's from the Gospel according to Philip.
听听这段，菲利浦福音书的一段
Philip?
菲利浦福音？
Yes, it was rejected at the Council of Nicaea...
是的，在尼西亚会议被抵制了
...along with any other gospels that made...
被抵制的福音还有很多
...Jesus appear human and not divine.
都因为书里耶稣像人不像神
"And the companion of the Savior is Mary Magdalene.
“救世主的同伴是抹大拉的玛丽”
Christ loved her more than all the disciples...
“基督爱她胜过爱所有的使徒”
...and used to kiss her on the..."
“他总是亲她的...”
But this says nothing of marriage.
但这里没说结婚啊
Well, actually...
这个嘛，事实上
Robert.
罗伯特
Actually, in those days, the word "companion" literally meant "spouse."
事实上，在那个时候 “同伴”一词指的是“伴侣”
And this is from the Gospel of Mary Magdalene herself.
还有玛丽自己的福音书
- She wrote a gospel? - She may have.
- 她也写了福音书？ - 她可能写了
- Robert, will you fight fair?
- 罗伯特，你不能公平地争论吗？ - 她只是可能写了
"And Peter said, 'Did he prefer her to us? '
“彼得说，他爱她胜过我们吗？”
And Levi answered:
利未答道
'Peter, I see you contending against a woman like an adversary.
“彼得，我觉得你把女人 看作对手来竞争”
If the Savior made her won'thy, who are you, indeed, to reject her?"'
“如果救世主觉得她好 你到底算什么，凭什么抵制她呢？”
Yes. And then, my dear, Jesus goes on to tell Mary Magdalene...
是的，那时，亲爱的 耶稣告诉抹大拉的玛丽
...that it's up to her to continue his Church.
应该由她来继承他的教会
Mary Magdalene, not Peter.
抹大拉的玛丽，不是彼得
The Church was supposed to be carried on by a woman.
教会本该由一个女人来继承
Few realize that Mary was descended from kings, just as her husband was.
很少人意识到玛丽是从王位上退下的 就好像她的丈夫做过的一样
Now, my dear, the word in French for Holy Grail.
还有，亲爱的，法语中代表圣杯的词
From the Middle English "Sangreal"...
来自于中古英语“Sangreal”...
...of the original Arthurian legend.
而这个词来自与最早的亚瑟王的传说
Now, as two words. Can you translate for our friend?
现在把它一分为二 你能为我们的朋友翻译一下吗？
Sang real, it means "royal blood."
Sang real，意思是王室血脉
When the legend speaks of the chalice that held the blood of Christ...
传说中圣杯盛的是耶稣的血
...it speaks in fact of the female womb that carried Jesus' royal bloodline.
它实际说的是一个女人的子宫 延续了耶稣的王室血脉
But how could Christ have a bloodline, unless...?
但基督怎么会有血脉的传承呢，除非
Mary was pregnant at the time of the Crucifixion.
基督上十字架时，玛丽已经怀孕了
For her own safety and for that of Christ's unborn child...
为了保护她的安全 和基督未出世的孩子
...she fled the Holy Land and came to France.
她逃出了圣地，来到了法国
And here, it is said, she gave birth to a daughter, Sarah.
在这，据说，她生了一个女儿，莎拉
They know the child's name.
他们还知道孩子的名字？
- A little girl. - Yes.
- 一个小女孩 - 是的
If that were true, it's adding insult to injury.
如果这是真的，简直就是伤口撒盐
Why?
为什么？
The pagans found transcendence through the joining of male to female.
异教徒们通过男女的结合 找寻超脱现实之路
People found God through sex?
人们通过性爱找寻上帝？
In paganism, women were worshiped as a route to heaven...
在异教中，女人被当作 通向天堂之路来崇拜
...but the modern Church has a monopoly on that...
但现代教会宣称只有
...in salvation through Jesus Christ.
耶稣基督的救赎才是通向天堂之路
And he who keeps the keys to heaven rules the world.
谁掌握了天堂的大门 就将统治世界
Women, then, are a huge threat to the Church.
女人，对教会的威胁很大
The Catholic Inquisition soon publishes...
天主教异端裁判所很快出版了
...what may be the most blood-soaked book in human history.
被称为人类历史上浸满最多鲜血的书
The Malleus Maleficarum.
《玛勒斯・玛累费卡姆》
The Witches' Hammer.
翻译过来就是《女巫之锤》
It instructed the clergy on how to locate, torture and kill...
它指导神职人员如何 寻找，折磨和杀戮
...all freethinking women.
一切有自由思想的女人
In three centuries of witch hunts...
在三个世纪的女巫搜寻中
...50,000 women are captured, burned alive at the stake.
五万女人被捕 在火刑柱上被活活烧死
Oh, at least that. Some say millions.
至少有这么多，有人说有数百万
Imagine, then, Robert...
想想看，罗伯特
...that Christ's throne might live on in a female child.
基督的血脉可能存在于一个女童身上
You asked what would be won'th killing for.
就凭这就足够血流成河的了
Witness the greatest cover-up in human history.
见证人类历史上最大的黑白颠倒
This is the secret that the Priory of Sion...
这就是郇山隐修会守护了 20个世纪的秘密
They are the guardians of the royal bloodline.
他们守护着王室血脉
The keepers of the proof of our true past.
守护着能证明真实历史的证据
They are the protectors of the living descendants of Jesus Christ...
守护着耶稣基督和玛丽 活着的后代
Sir Leigh?
雷爵士
Sometimes I wonder who is serving whom.
有时我简直怀疑谁是主谁是仆
His sauces are not that fantastic.
他的酱也不那么好吃
Yes, can I help you?
是我，有什么事？
Yes. They're on the news now.
他们正在上新闻
Living descendants? Is it possible?
活着的后代？这可能吗？
It's not impossible.
没什么不可能的
You have not been honest with me. Your pictures are on the television.
你骗了我，电视上播出了你的照片
You are wanted for four murders!
你被通缉杀了4个人
That's why Vernet said "killing spree."
这就是韦尔内所谓的“杀戮狂欢”
You come into my home, playing on my passions for the Grail.
你跑到我家，和我大谈圣杯
- That's why he needed you. - You will leave my house!
- 这就是他为什么需要你 - 你给我滚出去
- Leigh, listen! - No, I'm calling the police.
- 雷，听我说 - 不，我要给警察打电话
Jacques Sauniere was her grandfather.
雅克・索尼埃是她的祖父
You're the obsessive Priory scholar.
你狂热研究隐修会
You still keep lists of who might be in the Priory?
该有隐修会可能成员的名单吧
I'll bet Jacques Sauniere was on one of those lists.
我打赌雅克・索尼埃一定列在上面
He was on your list of who could be Grand Master, wasrt he?
你的名单上，他可能是“大师”对吧？
- What? - I'll bet he was right at the top.
- 什么？ - 我打赌他一定身处高位
Consider: Four men murdered? The same number as the guardians.
想想看：四人被杀，和守护者的数目一样
What if the Priory was compromised, the other senechaux dead?
如果隐修会被破坏了 其他长老都死了会怎样？
What if you yourself were dying, a Grand Master?
你要是个快死去的大师会怎样？
You'd have to pass the secret on to someone you could trust.
你得把秘密传给某个你能信任的人
Someone outside the society.
某个组织以外的人
Maybe someone whose training you had begun but never finished.
可能是你开始训练 但尚未结束的某人
Robert, your ruse is pathetic.
罗伯特，你的阴谋真是可怜
Not really.
不见得
No, that's impossible.
不，这不可能
Can that really...?
这难道真的是
Is it the keystone?
拱心石？
I'll even show it to you, Leigh.
我会展示给你看，雷
Will you just tell us what the hell it's for?
你能否告诉我们这到底是干什么的
Fache says to wait, so I wait.
法希说要等，所以我等
What's Fache thinking? The truck is here. They're inside.
法希在想啥？卡车在这，他们在里面
Yes.
是的
As the legend foretold:
如同传说的一样
"It hides beneath the Rose."
“它藏于玫瑰之下”
Oh, my.
哦，上帝
Leigh.
雷
Please.
请说
I'm sorry. Yes, of course.
对不起，当然
Inside the keystone...
在拱心石里面
...there'll be a map.
有一张地图
A map that will lead us to the Holy Grail.
指引我们去找圣杯的地图
To be trained by the Grand Master himself.
你接受大师本人的训练
Did he pass down the fleur-de-lis? Is that how you found this?
他有没有给你鸢尾花徽 你是不是就这么找到这的？
And he must have sung you the riddle songs.
他一定给你唱过谜语歌吧
I know some of them.
我知道一些
Can you keep secrets?
你能保守秘密吗？
Can you know a thing and never say it again?
你能永远不说你知道的一些事吗？
And codes?
还有密码？
I imagine they lie down for you like lovers.
我觉得它们就好像你的情人一样
A senechal. A guardian of the Grail right here in my own home.
一位大师，圣杯的守护人就在我家里
Tell him, please. I don't know any of this.
请告诉他，我对此一无所知
Leigh, it's not that simple. She doesn't rem...
雷，这没那么简单，她根本不...
Robert!
罗伯特
Do not move, woman.
别动，女人
Cripple.
瘸子
Put the box on the table.
把那盒子放桌上
What, this trifle?
啥，这个小东西？
Well, perhaps we can make a financial arrangement.
也许我们可以来点经济补偿
Put the keystone on the table.
把拱心石放到桌上
You will not succeed.
你不会成功的
Only the won'thy can unlock the stone.
只有合格的人才能打开它
Rip the gate down.
把门拉倒
Well, well, my dear.
哦，亲爱的
Sit down.
坐下
- Are you okay? - Yeah, yeah.
- 你还好吗？ - 是的，是的
- Are you? - Yeah.
- 你呢？ - 是的
Yes, well, make yourself useful, you French fool.
没错，出点力，你个法国笨蛋
Get something to restrain this monster.
找点东西来捆住这个禽兽
Above the joint.
在关节上面
Fortunately, a dragon most easy to slay.
幸运的是，这是最容易杀的龙
He's wearing a cilice.
他穿着粗布衣
- A what? - Well, look.
- 什么？ - 看
Inflicts pain so he can suffer as Christ suffered.
忍受疼痛，基督受过的苦他也要受
Not so common these days.
现在这日子这可不常见了
Opus Dei.
天主教事工会
Remy, take care of this.
雷米，处理一下这个
Fache is Opus Dei.
法希是天主教事工会的
The policeman who's chasing us. He wears the cross in the world.
那个追我们的警察 他戴着十字架
Robert.
罗伯特
Well, I must say, you two are anything but dull.
我必须得说，你们两个真是笨
Leigh?
雷？
You want what's in this box?
你想要盒子里面的东西吗？
We need a way out of here.
我们要找条路逃出去
Well, actually...
其实嘛
...I do have a plane.
我有架飞机
- Robert! Where do we go? - Come along.
- 罗伯特，我们去哪？ - 过来
- In here. Come in. - Over here.
- 这里，进来 - 这边
Get the door. Hurry.
开门，快点
Over here. Over here. Sophie.
这边，这边，索菲
Watch out!
注意
Be careful.
小心
Come, Rem...
来啊，雷米
Shit.
糟糕
Easy.
慢点
Jesus!
天啊
Apropos.
刚刚好
I can't imagine what your complaint is.
不明白你有什么好抱怨的
I'd be within my rights to shoot you and let you rot in my woods!
我完全可以杀了你，然后让你暴尸荒野
Put that away. We might need him.
把枪那开，我们可能还需要他
Better.
老实点
Opus Dei.
天主事工会
- What is it? - A conservative Catholic sect.
- 它到底是什么？ - 天主教的一个保守派
Opus Dei is a prelature to the Vatican.
是梵蒂冈的一个自治教团
You're saying the Vatican is killing people for this box?
你是说，梵蒂冈为了这个盒子而杀人？
No, no, no. Not the Vatican...
不，不，不，不是梵蒂冈
...and not Opus Dei, but we are in the middle of a war.
也不是天主事工会 我们卷入了这场战争
And one that has been going on forever.
并且这场战争从未停止
On the one side stands the Priory...
一边是隐修会
...and on the other an ancient group of despots...
另外一边是一个古老的专制组织
...with members hidden in high-ranking positions...
他的成员都任职于教会的高级职务
And this Council of Shadows tries to destroy proof of the bloodline.
这个隐蔽的组织 试图销毁关于血统的证据
And that throughout history, they seek out and kill...
这么多年来 他们一直寻找并杀死
...the living descendants of Jesus Christ.
还活着的耶稣后裔
- That's insane. - Is it?
- 这真荒谬 - 你这样认为么？
How many atrocities and scandals has the Catholic Church...
天主教会多年来做过多少暴行
...rationalized in its time? And what happens...
干过多少造谣中伤
...if some persuasive scientific evidence emerges that shows...
要是有可信的科学证据说明
...that the Church's version of Christ is inaccurate?
教会版本的基督和现实不符会怎样
What if the world discovers...
如果全世界发现
...that the greatest story ever told is actually a lie?
他们所熟知的信条只是一个谎言的时候
The Vatican faces a crisis of faith unprecedented.
梵蒂冈面临着一个空前的信任危机
I've got a signal now, sir. It's ringing.
先生，现在有信号了 有电话来了
Roger, look, I'm so sorry. I've got tired of the weather here in France...
罗杰，我很抱歉 我对法国这里的天气已经感觉到厌烦了
...and could you make the plane ready for...
你能为我准备一架飞机 去苏黎世吗？
Yes. No, we love Zurich.
是的，我们爱苏黎世
What the hell do you mean, you lost them? Collet.
你他妈的到底是什么意思，科莱 你追丢了？
You're the one who lost them.
是你追丢了
You control every step of this investigation.
这次调查你负责全局
You don't let anybody breathe.
你让人没有片刻喘息
You're acting like you lost your mind.
你简直像是失去理智了
What is it with these two birds?
这2个人到底拿了什么？
Interpol just registered a new flight plan from Le Bourget.
国际刑警组织刚刚 从布尔歇机场获得一个飞行计划
Stay out of my way on this, Collet.
别插手我的案子，科莱
Did you kill Jacques Sauniere?
是你杀了雅克・索尼埃吗？
I am the messenger of God.
我是上帝的使者
Did you kill my grandfather?
是你杀了我的爷爷吗？
Each breath you take is a sin.
汝之呼吸皆为罪恶
No shadow will be safe again.
任何阴影不能藏身
For you will be hunted by angels.
盖汝必遭天使追缉
You believe in God?
你相信上帝么？
Your God doesn't forgive murderers.
你的上帝不会原谅杀人犯的
He burns them.
他会烧死凶手的
Sophie.
索菲
The Teacher will be pleased.
“导师”会高兴的
What will you do once you have the Grail?
你拿到圣杯会怎么做？
Destroy it.
毁掉它
The documents and the sarcophagus, of course.
当然还有相关文献和石棺
And the heir?
还有他的后裔
Will you exercise the final edict? Spill his blood?
你会遵行最终法令吗？流尽他的血
There will be no need.
没有必要
Once the sarcophagus is destroyed, DNA testing will be impossible.
一旦石棺被毁 DNA测试就无法执行
There is no way to prove a living bloodline.
就没有办法证实存在活着的后裔了
But if you had to...
如果必须
...would you do as councils have done before us?
你会象组织以前做的那样做么？
Christ...
基督
Christ sacrificed his life for the betterment of humanity.
基督为救世而牺牲了自己的生命
So, too, may be the fate of his seed.
或许这也是他后人的命运
Robert.
罗伯特
When we land, you must go straight to your embassy.
我们一着陆，你必须直接去你的大使馆
Is that so?
是吗？
Don't you see it?
你还不懂吗？
They never wanted you.
他们根本不想抓你
Maybe even Fache didn't.
说不定连法希都不想
It's all about this...
这都是为了这个
...idiotic little box.
这个破盒子
That's not too flattering.
这可算不上夸奖
Crazy old man.
老疯子
Why leave me with this?
干嘛要留给我这个
I should just throw it away.
我真该把它扔掉
He trusted you, Sophie.
他信任你，索菲
A guardian of the Holy Grail.
圣杯的守护者
It sounds so stupid.
听起来真蠢
It's quite an honor, if you think about it...
这是项荣耀，如果你认真想
...and take it seriously.
认真信的话
He took it seriously enough to get himself killed.
他就是信得太认真才会被杀
Not him. You.
不是他，是你
He was the only family I knew.
他是我唯一的家人了
And maybe I didn't know him at all.
而可能我对他根本不了解
I'm his marionette, Robert.
我就是他的木偶，罗伯特
Like a girl again, just with no gift at the end.
现在又像是小女孩的时候了 就是没有礼物
But you've done enough.
不过你做的够多的了
I don't know why Sauniere picked me to help you, Sophie.
我不知道索尼埃为什么 选我来帮你，索菲
But I won't leave you alone in all this.
但我不会让你一个人面对这个的
Two marionettes, then.
那就是两个木偶
Maybe this is why he chose you.
说不定这就是他选你的原因
Because you will stay.
因为你会留下来
I need the flight plan.
我需要这个飞行计划
Ten minutes.
等10分钟
I asked you to get it for me.
我要你现在给我
I'm on break.
我正在休息
Come back in 10 minutes.
10分钟后再来吧
My nose! My nose!
我的鼻子，我的鼻子
The flight plan, please.
请给我飞行计划
You asshole!
你这个混蛋
It's not "cross."
不是“cross”
"Spear"?
“spear”吗？
What happened to her?
她怎么了？
No one knows.
没人知道
Mary Magdalene lived out her days in hiding.
抹大拉的玛丽余生都在躲藏
And the zealots pursued her still...
而狂热的信徒不停的寻找她的信息
...even in death, trying to destroy proof of her existence.
即使她死了，也试图毁掉她存在的证据
But she always had her Knights.
但是她有守护她的骑士
Brave men sworn to defend her.
勇敢的人们宣誓守护她
You see, to worship before her sarcophagus...
为了表示对她石棺的崇敬
...to kneel before the bones of Mary Magdalene...
他们跪在抹大拉的玛丽的遗体前
...was to remember all those who were robbed of their power...
为了记住那些被夺取了权力的人 受迫害的人
Ultimately, the Priory hid her remains and the proof of her bloodline...
最终，隐修会隐藏了她的遗体和她的后裔
...until most believed her sarcophagus...
直到大家都相信她的石棺
...the Holy Grail...
也就是圣杯
...was finally lost in time.
最终消失在历史长河
What are you doing?
你在干吗？
At the chateau, you said, "It hides beneath the Rose."
在庄园里，你说过 它藏在玫瑰之下
No, no, no. Do be careful.
不，不，不，小心
In Latin, sub rosa. Literal translation...
在拉丁语里，sub rosa翻译为
"Beneath the rose."
在玫瑰下
We need a mirror.
我们需要一面镜子
Backwards. In the style of Leonardo himself.
镜像文字 典型的达芬奇风格
Thank you.
谢谢
In London lies a knight a Pope interred
骑士葬于伦敦教皇主祭
His labor's fruit a Holy wrath incurred
他的行为触怒了上帝
You seek the orb that ought be on his tomb
寻找的宝球应在骑士墓里
It speaks of Rosy flesh and seeded womb
道破“玫瑰”之身与受孕子宫之秘
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred"?
骑士葬于伦敦教皇主祭
A knight whose funeral was presided over by the Pope.
一个骑士的葬礼是由教皇来主持的
Of course, the Priory knights were not just any knights.
当然，隐修会的骑士并非一般的骑士
Templars.
圣殿骑士
And there's just one place to bury a Templar knight in London.
在伦敦，只有一个地方会葬圣殿骑士
Temple Church.
圣殿教堂
If you'll excuse me, my dear...
亲爱的，请让一下
...Roger and I must discuss a change in flight plan.
我和罗杰必须讨论一下改变航线的问题了
Leigh.
雷
Harboring and transporting fugitives?
你藏匿并偷运了通缉犯
You are already implicated enough.
你已经被连累的够多的了
You and I, Robert, have observed history.
罗伯特，你和我一直在观察历史
Time has been our glass.
时间就是我们的眼镜
We are in history now. Living it.
而此刻我们就活在历史之中
Making it.
创造历史
"Lmplicated"?
连累？
I am on a Grail quest.
我正在寻找圣杯啊
Forgive me, Robert...
罗伯特，我不得不说
...but you two may well have given this old man...
你们俩可能给了这个老人
...the greatest night of his life.
一生中最伟大的一个夜晚
Thank you.
谢谢你们
He's going to want more money.
他可能会要更多的钱
I suppose this is a new technique for investigations.
我想这是调查的一种新技术吧
I've lost them. They flew to Switzerland.
他们跑了 他们飞去了瑞士
No extradition.
不能引渡
The controller filed charges. Ari was on dispatch. He called me.
那个调度员投诉了你，埃里被派来接替你 他给我打了电话
What's going on, Bezu?
怎么了，贝祖？
You know that I am Opus Dei?
你知道我是天主事工会的成员吧
Yes.
是的
A bishop of my order called me.
我们教派的一个主教打电话给我
He said a killer came to him in confession.
说一个杀人犯曾经去向他忏悔
His name was Robert Langdon.
他叫罗伯特・兰登
He said I couldn't imagine the evil in this mars heart.
他说你想象不到那人的内心有多邪恶
That he would keep killing.
他会继续杀人
He said I had to stop him.
他说，我必须阻止他
The bishop broke his vows to tell me this.
主教破戒告诉了我这些
He charged me to stop Robert Langdon.
他责令我去阻止罗伯特・兰登
Tell me, Collet, who have I failed?
告诉我，科莱，我让谁失望了？
The bishop?
主教？
God himself?
上帝？
They've changed their flight plan to London.
他们改变了航线去了伦敦
Go on, Fache. I'll take care of the controller.
去吧，法希，我来管塔台
Maybe he needs a few extra euros.
他可能会再要些欧元
Just tell me next time.
下次先告诉我
I have them, tower. Relay Hawker to land and hold on tarmac.
我发现他们了，塔台 让飞机降落，停在停机坪上
- Secure the area! - Wider!
- 包围他们 - 过去那边
- Armed police! - You two, round the back!
- 警察 - 你们2个，绕后面去
Armed police! Put your hands in the air!
警察，举起手来
- Three men up! - Ready!
- 上去3个人 - 准备
Put your hands in the air! Do it now!
举起手来，快点
I'm afraid that's easier said than done in my case.
对我来讲说着容易做起来难啊
Oh, good morning.
哦，早上好
Did that old cannabis charge finally catch up with me?
难道是我以前抽大麻被发现了？
Sir, the French police say you're transporting fugitives...
先生，法国警方说你飞机上有通缉犯
...and you may have a hostage onboard.
你飞机上可能还藏有一名人质
I'm to take you all into custody.
我要把你们都抓起来
Sadly, I have an important medical appointment which I can't miss.
对不起，我和医生约好了，而且不能迟到
I'll fetch the car, sir.
我去把车开过来，先生
This is serious, sir. The French police are on their way. Stop!
这很严重，先生 法国警方已经在路上了，别动
Inspector, I can't afford the time to indulge your games.
检查官，我没时间陪你玩什么把戏
I'm late and I'm leaving.
我已经迟到了，我得走了
If it's so important for you to stop us...
如果你非要阻止
...then you're just going to have to shoot us.
就朝我开枪吧
You can start with him.
你可以先杀了他
Search the plane.
搜查飞机
All right.
好吧
I could run them over.
我可以冲出去
Bad tip.
消息不准
Let him go.
让他们走吧
The French cannot be trusted.
法国人不值得相信
Everyone comfy?
大家都好么？
Biscuits?
要饼干？
They didn't notice anything?
他们没发现么？
Well, people rarely notice things right in front of their eyes, don't you find?
你没发现，人很少注意到 眼前的东西么？
Do you have the bonds, bishop?
你拿到债券了么，主教？
Yes, I do, Teacher.
是的，“导师”
I have chosen an Opus Dei residence for the exchange.
我选了个天主事工会的住处 我们在那交换
I am honored.
这是我的荣幸
By the time you get to London, I will have the Grail.
等你到了伦敦，我就会有圣杯了
- I take it the news is good, then. - I fly to London.
- 就是说是好消息了 - 我会飞去伦敦
The Teacher is waiting for me there.
“导师”在那等我
He has chosen a house of Opus Dei to make the exchange.
他选了一座天主事工会的房子来作交易
Mere currency for the location of the Grail.
仅仅是钱就能买到圣杯的位置
Imagine it.
想想看吧
Remember, if we are discovered by the Vatican, we are excommunicated.
记住，如果我们被梵蒂冈发现 我们会被逐出教会的
- So should anything go wrong... - Yes, I know, I know.
- 所以，如果出了什么问题 - 是的，我知道，我知道
This council does not exist.
这个组织并不存在
As it never has.
并且从未有过
Old friend. Heaven protect you.
老朋友，天堂保佑你
Keep an eye out for the police.
小心警察
I must say, Robert, I'm quite impressed...
我不得不说，罗伯特 我很惊讶
...by the way you withstood my little aeroplane.
你一路忍受着我的小飞机
Did he never tell you?
他没告诉过你么？
When he was a boy, young Robert fell into a well.
他还是个孩子的时候 小罗伯特掉进了一个井里
How old were you?
你那时多大？
Seven.
7岁
Treading water all night long, screaming his lungs out...
他踩了一晚上的水 大声的呼救
...to the echoes screaming back.
但没人听到
When they found him, he was nearly catatonic.
当人们发现他的时候 他已经快发疯了
Help!
救命啊
It was a long time ago.
这是很久以前的事了
Oh, now, now, Robert.
哦，罗伯特
You above all people shouldn't be one to dismiss the influence of the past.
毕竟人们很难摆脱过去的阴影
Temple Church. I always forget it's right here.
圣殿教堂，我差不多忘了它就在这了
Built 1185 and modern London just sprang up right around it.
建于1185年，现代的伦敦差不多 就是围着它建起来的
Tell me, why has the Priory kept the Grail location secret all these years?
告诉我为什么隐修会这些年来 一直隐藏着圣杯位置
I don't know.
我不知道
Some say the Priory wait for the heir to reveal himself...
有人说隐修会在等待耶稣后裔的出现
...which is especially odd...
...这种情况很不现实...
...since legend suggests he may not know his own true identity.
因为据传说他自己也不知道他的身份
Hello?
有人吗？
Why do they make them so scary?
为什么他们把这里弄的这么阴森
Oh, it's cold.
哦，真冷啊
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
骑士葬于伦敦教皇主祭
So which tomb has an orb?
那么哪个坟墓有圆球呢？
Those knights with their legs crossed...
那些交叉双腿的骑士
...means they'd been to the Holy Land.
表示他们去过圣地
Two wear tunics over their armor...
2个人在盔甲外穿着外罩
...and two have full-length robes.
2个人穿着长袍
Two are grasping swords.
2个人拿着剑
And one... Two are praying.
还有1个...2个人在祈祷
This one has his arms at his sides.
这个人把他的武器放在身旁
Oh, and this poor fellow has almost disappeared entirely.
哦，这个可怜的家伙几乎被磨光了
I don't see any orb that ought be on a tomb.
我没在坟墓上看到什么圆球
"Ought be on his tomb." Are we looking for a missing orb?
应在骑士墓里 是不是圆球不见了？
Maybe.
或许，看那边
These aren't tombs.
这不是坟墓
- What? Yes, of course they are. - No.
- 什么？是的，他们当然是的 - 不
- They're effigies. - What?
- 他们是雕像 - 什么？
Not tombs. There's no bodies here.
不是坟墓，里面没有尸体
This place is wrong.
这个地方不对
Can we go now? We should go.
我们现在可以走么？ 我们应该走了
Sophie! No!
索菲，不
Where is the keystone?
拱心石在哪？
Do not test me!
别耍我
- Let her go! - Don't hurt her.
- 放开她 - 别伤害她
Give me the keystone! Give it to me!
把拱心石给我，给我
Here! Here! Here it is! Here it is.
这里，这里，在这里，在这里
Just let her go, and you and I can... We'll come to some agreement.
放开她吧，我们可以做个交易
Remy.
雷米
Remy. No, no, no. No, put it away.
雷米，不，不，把枪放下
Put it away. They're too close together. You don't have a clear shot.
把枪放下，他们靠的太近了 你射不准的
- Yes, I do. - What do you think you're doing?
- 我当然会射准的 - 你到底想干吗？
Thank you, professor. For a moment, this was getting complicated.
谢谢你，教授 这一刻，你肯定很迷惑
Oh, this is absurd. Oh, for God's sake, man!
哦，这真荒谬 看在上帝的份上
That was satisfying.
现在满意了吧
I'm glad this bullshit is over.
很高兴这破事终于结束了
Throw Teabing in the trunk.
把提彬扔进后背箱里
What?
什么？
Here. You okay?
来，你还好吗？
Sorry.
对不起
I don't think he's following.
我想他没跟来
They won't kill Leigh until they find the Grail.
他们不会杀死雷 除非他们找到圣杯
- So we have to find it before they do. - I have to get to a library, fast.
- 我们必须在他们之前找到圣杯 - 我必须尽快去图书馆
Lieutenant!
队长
One flag off the prints.
新资料
Remy Legaludec.
雷米・利加路迪
Petty theft.
小偷
Skipped out on a hospital bill for a tracheotomy.
在医院做气管切开术时逃出去了
Peanut allergy.
花生酱过敏
Like Marie.
像玛丽一样
This way. Marie?
这边走，玛丽？
My daughter.
我的女儿
Over here.
到这来
Where?
哪里？
Up there.
上面
What's all that?
那都是什么？
Very advanced surveillance.
非常先进的监测设备
It's a listening post.
这是个监听点
Get me Fache.
给我找法希
Four of these names are the men killed last night.
这上面有四个名字就是昨晚被杀的四个
He once whined to me about the wasted space of so large a trunk.
他曾经向我抱怨过后背箱太大了
Let's see if he complains so now.
让我们看看他现在还那么抱怨不
Are you the Teacher?
你是“导师”么？
I am.
是的
Superbly done. You've been of great service.
干的很好 你表现了你对主的忠诚
The cryptex has yet to be opened. I can still serve.
拱心石还没打开 我还能继续为主服务
You've done enough.
你已经做的够多的了
We cannot let ego deter us from our goal.
决不允许个人恩怨 阻止我们实现目标
I understand.
我明白
Good.
很好
Wait here, at this house of Opus Dei, and you will be rewarded.
在这里等我，在天主事工会的住处里 你会受到嘉奖的
I will dispose of the old man.
我会处理那个老头的
Bless you, Silas.
愿主保佑你，塞拉斯
Teacher.
“导师”
Christ be with you.
主与你同在
We're at least a half-hour to Chelsea Library.
我们去切尔西图书馆需要半个小时
If we're gonna help Leigh, that's too long.
如果我们想救雷，时间恐怕不够
Where you going?
你去哪里？
Getting you a library card.
给你弄张图书卡
Excuse me. May I sit next to you?
请问，我能坐在你旁边么？
- Yeah, sure. - Thank you.
- 当然可以 - 谢谢
That's great.
很好
Didrt say you had a boyfriend.
你没说你有男朋友的
Thanks.
谢谢
Let's see if we can access the database on this.
让我们看看能不能用这个进入数据库
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
骑士葬于伦敦教皇主祭
Compounding keywords:
输入关键字
Knight, Pope, Grail.
骑士，教皇，圣杯
Your precious treasure was almost lost, and with it, my fortune.
你差点失去了你的宝贝 那我的钱也就没了
Can you believe how well I did?
你觉得我演的怎么样？
I even convinced the monk.
我甚至骗过了那个修道士
I should be in theater.
我应该去当演员
A toast to our success, Teacher. The end of the journey is near.
预祝我们的成功，“导师” 我们的旅程就快结束了
Your identity shall go with me to the grave.
我死也不会说出你的身份的
There's your problem, mate. It's your basic linguistic coincidence.
伙计，这不对，你刚好碰上多义词
See, keywords keep coming up with the writings...
这是用你关键字找到的
...of some bloke named Alexander Pope.
全是亚历山大・蒲柏
"A. Pope."
一位教皇 （也是亚历山大・蒲柏的缩写）
Your grandfather was a genius.
你的爷爷是个天才
Come on.
快来
Emergency. Which service do you require?
报警中心 有什么可以帮你
I know the location of two murderers wanted by French police.
我知道法国警方通缉的2个凶手在哪里
We've just had a 999 call.
我们刚接到一个报警电话
Triangulation leads back to Docklands.
三角定位显示那是在港区
Caller was male. Claimed your two murderers...
打电话的是名男子 说你们通缉的2个凶手
...are hiding at an Opus Dei house.
躲在一个天主事工会的住处里
The knight we're looking for is Sir Isaac Newton.
我们要找的骑士是艾撒克・牛顿爵士
His life's work produced new sciences that incurred the wrath of the Church.
他在科学上的新发现触怒了天主教会
Gravity, for God sakes.
重力论
And if you choose to believe...
你知道吗
...he was also a Grand Master of the Priory as well.
他还是郇山隐修会的大师
But if he offended the Catholic Church...
但是如果他冒犯了天主教会
...the Pope would be the last person to preside over his funeral.
教皇是不会为他主持葬礼的
Well, that's where I got it wrong.
这是我们误解的地方
"In London lies a knight a Pope interred."
“骑士葬于伦敦教皇主祭”
Sir Isaac Newtors funeral was presided over...
艾撒克・牛顿爵士的葬礼是由
...by his good friend, his colleague, Alexander Pope.
他的好朋友兼同事亚历山大・蒲柏主持的 （蒲柏就是教皇的意思）
A. Pope. His first initial. How did I miss that?
亚历山大・蒲柏，他的首字母是A 我怎么忘了这个
Here.
这里
Yes. Isaac Newtors tomb.
对，艾撒克・牛顿的坟墓
An orb.
一个圆球
Yes. Which one? It's not possible to tell if a particular orb is missing.
是的，哪一个？ 有哪个星体给漏掉了呢？
"An orb with Rosy flesh and seeded womb."
道破“玫瑰”之身与受孕子宫之秘
Solar system. The planets. Constellations. Signs of the zodiac.
太阳系，行星，星座，黄道十二宫
See, our moon is missing.
瞧，这里没有我们的月球
The moons of Saturn and Jupiter. They're not here.
土星和木星的卫星也没有
Eyes of the cherubs themselves?
是小天使的眼睛么？
Robert. These tracks.
罗伯特，这些脚印
Look at the cane marks in the dust.
看上去像是拄拐杖的人的
Teabing was here.
提彬来过这里
He was alone.
他一个人
When the two of you arrived at my home as you did...
你们来拜访我
...others might call it God's will.
人们会说这是上帝的旨意
I believed that if I had the cryptex...
我以为如果密码筒在我手上
...I could solve the riddle alone.
我自己就可以破解那谜语
But I was unwon'thy.
但我不行
But you...
但你...
You have a reason to be here.
你来这里并非无因
You're the last remaining guardian of the Grail.
你是圣杯最后的守护者
Your grandfather and the other senechaux...
你祖父和他的长老们
...would not have lied with dying breath...
不知道秘密能被守住的话
...unless they knew their secret was preserved.
是不会甘心就戮的
How could you know Sauniere's last words?
你是怎么知道索尼埃遗言的？
Leigh.
雷
Grail quests require sacrifice.
找寻圣杯必然要做出牺牲
You are a murderer.
你是凶手
No. No. Robert, tell her.
不，不，罗伯特，告诉她
When history is written, murderers are heroes.
当历史写就之时，凶手就成了英雄
You self-righteous bastard!
你这个自以为是的混蛋
We need to just walk away.
我们要做的是离开这儿
- No, don't. Don't. - Walk away.
- 别走，别走 - 走开
I'll do what I have to now.
如果必须我什么都能做
Anything.
任何事情
Do you understand?
你们明白了吗？
So now...
那么现在
...can't we all be friends again?
我们又是老朋友了，对吗？
This way.
这边
I'm going to put this gun down. I only want you both to listen.
我会放下我的枪 我只想让你们俩好好听着
I'm listening now.
我正在听
For 2000 years...
两千年来
...the Church has rained oppression and atrocity upon mankind...
教会对人类做出无数的压迫和暴行
...crushed passion and idea alike, all in the name of their walking God.
摧毁人们的热情和思想 都是以上帝的名义
Proof of Jesus' mortality can bring an end to all that suffering...
证明耶稣的人性可以结束这一切痛苦
...drive this church of lies to its knees.
拆穿教会的谎言
Armed police!
警察
Drop your weapon!
扔掉你的武器
Stop, Silas!
停手，塞拉斯
We are betrayed, my son.
我们被出卖了，我的孩子
The living heir must be revealed.
活着的后裔一定要被找到
Jesus must be shown for what he was.
耶稣本来的面目一定要被揭露
Not miraculous, simply man.
他不是神，而是一个普通的人
I'm sorry.
对不起
Armed police!
警察
Drop your weapon! Drop it! Drop it!
扔掉武器，扔掉
Put it down now! Put it down!
现在扔掉武器，扔掉
I am a ghost.
我是一个鬼魂
The dark con can be exposed.
黑暗的欺骗终会被揭露
Mankind can finally be set free, and we can do it, Robert.
人类最终将获得自由 我们可以做到的，罗伯特
The three of us.
我们3个
How is Silas?
塞拉斯怎么样了？
Is he...? Is he alive?
他...他还活着吗？
The monk?
修道士？
Bishop, how would you know this killer's name?
主教，你怎么知道凶手的名字的？
Get me out of here, Fache.
帮我离开这，法希
Wait.
等等
Langdon never came to you in confession, did he?
兰登从未向你忏悔过，对吗？
One of your followers called you about the crime-scene photos.
你的一个同僚告诉了你犯罪现场的照片
I cannot be implicated here. There are still important works to be done.
我不能在这里耽搁 还有重要的事在等着我去做
You used me.
你利用了我
God uses us all.
所有的事情都是神指引我们去做的
Help me, Fache.
帮帮我，法希
Take him.
把他带走
- Did you get his cell phone? - Yes, sir.
- 你有他的手机么？ - 是的，先生
I'm going to need a trace.
我需要一些线索
Your Silas is dead.
你的塞拉斯已经死了
The Priory's sacred charge...
郇山隐修会的使命
...was to reveal the heir at the dawn of the new millennium.
是在千禧年来临时找到这个后裔
The millennium came and went and the living heir remained hidden.
而如今千禧年已经过了 活着的后裔仍然是个秘密
The Priory failed in their sacred charge.
隐修会辜负了他们的使命
So, what choice did I have?
那么我有什么选择呢？
I sought out the enemy.
我找到了敌人
I persuaded them, the Council of Shadows, that I was an ally.
我说服了那个黑暗理事会 说自己是他们的同盟
I even asked them for money so they would never suspect me.
我甚至向他们要过钱 所以，他们从未怀疑过我
Rector, I made them call me.
“导师”，我让他们叫我
"Teacher."
导师
- Why don't you and l... - No.
- 为什么你不和我... - 不
Robert, no words. On your knees.
罗伯特，别说话，跪下
Do it.
快点跪下
No, I mean it. Down.
不，我是说真的，跪下
Not you. No, my dear, you...
你不用，亲爱的，你...
You're my miracle, Sophie.
你是我的奇迹，索菲
You're the guardian of the Grail.
你是圣杯的守护者
All the oppression of the poor and the powerless...
那些贫苦无助的
...of those of different skin, of women.
不同肤色的女性受的压迫
You can put an end to all that.
可以由你一手终结
You must explode the truth onto the world.
你必须向世界揭露真相
It's your duty.
这是你的使命
You know the answer to this riddle.
你知道这个密码的答案
Open the cryptex...
打开拱心石
...and I'll put down the gun.
我就放下我的枪
I have no idea how.
我不知道该怎么打开
I don't know the code.
我不知道密码
And even if I did, I wouldn't tell you.
即使我知道，我也不会告诉你
Like your grandfather, then.
那就像你的爷爷那样
Willing to die for your secret.
为了你们的秘密去死
But by the way you've been looking at your hero...
那么你现在看看你的英雄
...I wonder, would you let him die for you?
我在想，你是否希望他为你而死？
Open it, Sophie, to save his life.
打开它，索菲，为了救他的命
- Leigh, you can't just... - Open the cryptex.
- 雷，你不能 - 打开拱心石
I don't know how.
我不知道怎么打开
Open it or he dies.
你不打开它，他就会死
- I swear, I don't know. - Do it! Do it!
- 我发誓，我真的不知道 - 快点打开，快点
- Stop it! - I don't know!
- 别那样做 - 我不知道
Stop it!
别吵
She can't do it, Leigh.
她打不开，雷
But give me a moment.
但是，给我点时间
Robert.
罗伯特
What are you doing?
你要干吗？
Please.
别说话
I'm sorry.
对不起
No!
不
No, Robert!
不，罗伯特
Oh, the map. It's ruined.
哦，地图被毁掉了
The map is ruined.
地图被毁掉了
The Grail.
圣杯
It's lost.
找不到了
The Grail is gone.
圣杯找不到了
Only the won'thy find the Grail, Leigh.
只有合格的人才能找到圣杯，雷
You taught me that.
你告诉我的
Armed police!
警察
Drop it! Drop your weapon!
扔掉你的武器，扔掉它
Put the gun down.
放下你的枪
That one. The old man.
那家伙，那个老头
You're under arrest!
你被捕了
You do not have to say anything, but it may harm your defense...
你有权保持沉默，但这样
...if you do not mention, when questioned...
可能会对你的辩护不利，如果你的询问
...something which you later rely on in court.
将来在法庭出现
Anything you do say will be given in evidence.
你所说的都将会作为呈堂证供
I'll have some questions for you.
我要问你一些问题
Big crowd out there now.
那的人真不少啊
Thank you for your statements. You are free to go, of course.
谢谢你的证词，当然你自由了
I'm sorry. You thought he was your friend, no?
对不起，你以为他曾是你们的朋友，对吧
It wasrt only us, was it?
不仅仅是我们
He used you too.
他也利用了你
Leave us, please.
请离开一下
I should have been smarter.
我应该聪明点的
I acted on faith, I suppose.
我想我只是凭信仰在办事
I'm sorry.
对不起
How many?
几个人被杀了？
Your grandfather, the other three, maybe more.
你的祖父，还有另外三人 可能还有更多
The monk was given to Teabing as a gift, it seems.
那个修道士似乎是作为礼物给提彬的
To do as he asked.
他让做什么就做什么
Teabing killed the servant himself, you know.
提彬杀了那个仆人
- Remy? - Yes.
- 雷米？ - 是的
By poison.
用毒
How much of it have you been able to figure out?
你查出了多少？
Some. Not enough for it to make sense.
一些，但还不足以联系起来让人理解
It won't ever make sense.
这永远不可能被理解
I'm sorry.
对不起
He forgot everything we've learned.
我们学过的一切他都忘了
Everything we teach.
我们教过的一切他都忘了
It's why we study history.
这就是我们研究历史的原因
So we'll stop killing each other.
为了让我们不再相互残杀
Robert! Robert! Robert! How could you do it?
罗伯特！罗伯特！罗伯特 你怎么能...
How could you? Robert!
罗伯特，你怎么能...
To destroy our hope of freedom.
毁掉了我们自由的希望
To deny every pilgrim the chance to kneel at the tomb of the Magdalene.
毁掉了每个朝圣者向抹大拉朝圣的机会
How could you?
你怎么能？
You couldn't! You solved it.
你不会的，你破解了密码
You took the scroll out before it broke!
你在毁掉之前，已经把地图拿出来了
You solved it. Oh, you'll find it, Robert. You'll find it. You know what to do.
你破解了密码，罗伯特 你会找到圣杯的，你知道该怎么做
You'll find the Grail, you'll kneel before her...
你会找到圣杯的 你会在她的坟墓前跪下
...and you'll set her free upon the world!
并向世界揭露真相
That man there, he's got the map to the Holy Grail!
那个人，他有圣杯的地图
There was every orb conceivable on that tomb except one:
那座坟墓上有各种各样的圆球 唯独没有
The orb which fell from the heavens and inspired Newtors life's work.
从天堂上掉下来的圆球 给了牛顿在科学上的灵感的圆球
Work that incurred the wrath of the Church until his dying day.
他有生之年在科学上的贡献 让天主教会很愤怒
A-P-P-L-E.
A-P-P-L-E
Apple.
苹果
The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits
圣杯在古老的罗斯林下静待
The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates
剑刃圣杯守护她的门宅
Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies
与大师的杰作相拥入梦
She rests at last beneath the starry skies
漫天星光下她终可入眠
I think I know where she's gone.
我想我知道她在哪里了
I think the Grail has gone home.
我想圣杯已经回家了
Built by the Templars themselves. Named for the original Rose Line.
由圣殿骑士自己建造 因古老的玫瑰线而得名
Rosslyn Chapel.
罗斯林教堂
So this is it.
看来就是这里了
The gift at the end.
最终的宝藏
"The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits."
圣杯在古老的罗斯林下静待
You never told me the joke Sauniere made of you.
你从未告诉过我 索尼埃和你开的玩笑
What was it?
是什么？
He called me a flatfoot.
他叫我警察
A beat cop of history.
史学界的警察
Oh, a dumb policeman...
哦，一个笨警察
...who just does his job day after day, of history.
每天总是探寻历史
You know, his father was one. A policeman.
你知道吗，他父亲就是一个警察
Sauniere said he was the most honorable man he had ever known.
索尼埃说他是最值得尊敬的人
We are who we protect, I think.
我想，我们就是我们要保护的人
What we stand up for.
我们为谁出头呢？
Jewish...
犹太人
...Christian, Egyptian...
基督徒，埃及人
...Masonic, pagan...
共济会会员，异教徒
...Templar crosses...
圣殿骑士的十字架
...pyramids.
金字塔
I think I've been here before.
我想我来过这
Sophie.
索菲
A very long time ago.
很久很久以前
Come along, Sophie.
过来，索菲
Sophie.
索菲
Over here.
来这里
"The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates."
剑刃圣杯守护她的门宅
Pagan symbols for male and female.
象征男性和女性的异教徒标记
Fused as one.
合为一体
As the pagans would have wanted.
就像异教徒希望的那样
We're about to close, I'm afraid.
不好意思，我们要关门了
We're just gonna be a moment.
我们就只待一会
Robert.
罗伯特
I've never seen that before.
我以前从没见过这些
The style is...
这个风格
It's unmistakable.
决不可能搞错
These could have been painted by Leonardo da Vinci.
这可能是列奥纳多・达・芬奇画的
"Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies."
与大师的杰作相拥入梦
"She rests at last beneath the starry skies."
漫天星光下她终可入眠
The fleur-de-lis.
鸢尾花纹章
She was here.
她曾经在这里
Her sarcophagus.
她的石棺
Mary Magdalene.
抹大拉的玛丽
The Holy Grail herself.
也就是圣杯
She was here.
她曾经在这里
With modern DNA testing, those bones...
用现代的DNA检测，那些遗骨
...could have shown definitive proof of a bloodline.
可以提供血脉的绝对证据
Where did she go?
她去了哪里？
Did the Church finally get her?
教会最后找到她了么？
This is incredible. Look at this.
真难以置信，瞧这里
Look at this. These records go back thousands of years.
瞧这里，这些记录可以追溯到几千年前
They date back to the death of Christ.
可以追溯到基督死的时候
Good God, could these really be the Grail documents?
天啊，这些难道真的是圣杯文献么？
What did he want from us? To find her sarcophagus?
他想让我们干吗？ 去寻找她的石棺么？
How was I ever supposed to figure all this out?
他怎么知道我能解开所有的秘密
When you and your grandfather fought...
当你和你的爷爷争吵的时候
...was it something about your past?
有没有提到你的过去？
How could you know that?
你怎么知道的？
About how your parents died?
关于你父母的死？
Sophie?
索菲
It was during primary school.
那时我还在上小学
I was in his library.
我在他的图书馆里
Doing research.
查找信息
I was trying to find out about my family.
我试图找到我的家人
Sophie, where are you, princess?
索菲，你在哪里，我的公主？
I wanted to know about them.
我想知道他们
But I couldn't find any records.
但我找不到任何信息
Not of their death...
关于他们的死
...not of the accident.
关于那起车祸
I'd asked him for as long as I could remember...
从我记事，我就不断询问他
...but he would never tell me.
但他从不告诉我
I told you, no.
我告诉过你，不要找
But why can't I?
但是为什么？
He stood over me...
他向我吼叫
...and he wouldn't let me leave.
不让我离开
They're dead. Dead and buried.
他们已经死了，已经下葬了
Never look for them, Sophie.
别再找他们了，索菲
Promise me.
答应我
Swear it!
发誓
Swear it to me!
向我发誓
I kept my promise.
我遵守了我的誓言
The next week he sent me to boarding school.
第二周，他把我送去了寄宿学校
One weekend I came home unexpectedly.
在一个周末 我没通知他就回家
And what I saw my grandfather doing...
我看到我的爷爷正在...
Some ritual.
进行某种仪式
I was so frightened.
我吓坏了
We hardly ever spoke again.
我们后来几乎没有说过话
Do you have any memories of your grandfather before the accident?
在那起车祸之前 你对你的爷爷有印象么？
Before your parents were killed?
在你的父母被杀之前
Yeah. No. I don't know.
有的，不，没有，我不知道
Why?
怎么了？
Because I don't think he was your grandfather.
因为我觉得他不是你爷爷
These are my parents.
这是我的父母
My brother.
这是我的哥哥
And this is you, isn't it?
这个是你，对吗？
The paper says the entire family was killed.
报纸说全家人都被杀了
The mother, the father, the boy, 6...
母亲，父亲，6岁的男孩
...and the girl, 4.
和4岁的女孩
But your name was never Sauniere. It's Saint-Clair.
但是你的不姓索尼埃 你姓圣克莱尔
It's one of the oldest families in France.
这是法国的一个古老的家族
It's from a line of the Merovingian kings.
是墨洛温王室的后裔
Royal blood.
王室血统
I was so wrong.
我错的很离谱
Sauniere didn't want you to help guard the secret of the Holy Grail.
索尼埃不是想让你守护圣杯的秘密
Sophie...
索菲
...you are the secret.
你就是这个秘密
You survived the accident.
你在那起车祸中幸存
If it even was an accident.
也可能那不是一起车祸
The Priory found out.
隐修会发现了你
Somehow they concealed the fact that you were alive.
他们隐藏了你幸存的事实
They hid you with the Grand Master himself...
他们把你藏在大师那里
...who raised you as his own.
他把你养育成人
According to all of this...
如果是这样的话
...Princess Sophie...
索菲公主
...you are the heir.
你就是那个后裔
The end of the bloodline.
你继承了血统
You are the last living descendent...
你是最后一个活着的耶稣基督的后裔
What is this?
这是干什么？
Sophie?
索菲
Who are you?
你们是谁？
There have been many names.
我们有很多名字
The keepers.
看守人
Guardians.
保卫者
The Priory of Sion.
郇山隐修会
But to you, Sophie, we are friends of the man who raised you:
但对于你，索菲，我们是 养育你成人的那个男人的朋友
Jacques Sauniere.
雅克・索尼埃
He would have wanted you to know that he loved you very much.
他想让你知道他是多么的爱你
And that the Priory are here to protect you now...
现在隐修会在这里保护着你
...as they have always protected our family.
就像他们一直保护我们家族
I gave you up once...
我曾经放弃过你
...knowing I might never see you again.
以为再也见不到你
I'm your grandmother, Sophie.
我是你的奶奶，索菲
I have prayed for this moment for a very long time.
为了这一刻，我等了很久了
Welcome home, child.
欢迎回家，孩子
Hey.
嘿
No more strings.
没有约束了
His last breath to keep me safe.
他的遗愿就是我的平安
She has some things she wants to tell me.
她想告诉我一些事情
About my family.
关于我的家庭
What will you do?
你打算怎么做？
The legend will be revealed when the heir reveals himself.
当找到耶稣后裔的时候 真相将被揭露
They just got the pronoun wrong.
只是他们以为后裔是男的
She said when Sauniere died...
她说在索尼埃死后
...he took the location of Mary's sarcophagus with him.
没人知道抹大拉的玛丽的石棺在哪了
So there's no way to empirically prove that I am related to her.
所以，没有办法证明我和她的血缘关系了
What would you do, Robert?
你下一步打算干吗，罗伯特?
Okay, maybe there is no proof. Maybe the Grail is lost forever.
好吧，或许没有证据 或许圣杯永远找不到了
But, Sophie, the only thing that matters is what you believe.
但是，索菲，重要的是你的信仰
History shows us Jesus was an extraordinary man...
历史告诉我们耶稣曾经是一个伟大的人
...a human inspiration. That's it.
激发了人类的灵性
That's all the evidence has ever proved.
仅此而已，证据仅仅证明了这些
But...
但是
...when I was a boy...
在我很小的时候
When I was down in that well Teabing told you about...
在我掉进井里的时候 就是提彬提起过的那次
...I thought I was going to die, Sophie.
我以为我会死掉，索菲
What I did...
我所能做的
...I prayed.
就是祈祷
I prayed to Jesus to keep me alive...
我向耶稣祈祷，希望他能让我活下去
...so I could see my parents again...
于是，我又见到了我的父母
...so I could go to school again...
我又回到了学校
...so I could play with my dog.
我又能和我的狗一起玩了
Sometimes I wonder if I wasrt alone down there.
有时我在想我不是一个人在井里
Why does it have to be human or divine?
为什么必须区分人或神呢？
Maybe human is divine.
或许人本身就是神
Why couldn't Jesus have been a father...
为什么耶稣不是一个父亲
...and still been capable of all those miracles?
并能创造所有奇迹呢？
Like turning water into wine?
就像把水变成了酒
Well, who knows? His blood is your blood.
谁知道呢 他的血在你身上流动
Maybe that junkie in the park will never touch a drug again.
或许那个公园里的瘾君子 会从此远离毒品
Maybe you healed my phobia with your hands.
或许你用你的双手治好了我的恐惧
And maybe you're a knight on a Grail quest.
或许你就是守护圣杯的骑士
Well, here's the question:
那么，问题就在于
A living descendent of Jesus Christ...
一个活着的耶稣的后裔
...would she destroy faith?
她会毁掉人们的信仰么？
Or would she renew it?
还是会让它重生
So again I say, what matters is what you believe.
我要再次重申，重要的是你的信仰
Thank you.
谢谢你
For bringing me here.
谢谢你把我带到这里
For letting him choose you...
谢谢你让他选择了我
...Sir Robert.
罗伯特爵士
You take care.
保重
Yes.
好的
Hey.
嘿
Nope.
不行
Maybe I'll do better with the wine.
或许我能比变酒做的更好
Godspeed.
祝你成功
Bloodline.
血统
Rose Line.
玫瑰线
"Hides beneath the Rose."
藏在玫瑰之下
"The Holy Grail 'neath ancient Roslin waits.
圣杯在古老的罗斯林下静待 (罗斯林是玫瑰线的音译)
Adorned in masters' loving art, she lies.
与大师的杰作相拥入梦
The blade and chalice guarding o'er her gates.
剑刃圣杯守护她的门宅
She rests at last beneath starry skies."
漫天星光下她终可入眠